<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="CreatingandPropagatingaSpacecraft"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Propagating a Spacecraft</title>

  <section>
    <title>Objective and Overview</title>

    <para>The objective of this tutorial is to learn how to create a
    spacecraft and a propagator, and then propagate the spacecraft to the
    desired position - in this example, to the orbit periapsis. The meaning of
    the term "propagate" here is simulating the spacecraft travel from its
    initial position until some given condition is met - for example, a
    predefined location or elapsed time. (See the GMAT Help module for more
    detail.) We perform this simulation by following the basic steps below.
    (Here and elsewhere, unless specified further, "click" will mean
    "left-click" of your computer cursor):</para>

    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Configure the resources - create a spacecraft and define its
        epoch and orbital elements.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Create and configure a propagator.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Modify the default Orbit View to visualize the spacecraft
        trajectory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configure the mission sequence to propagate the spacecraft to
        the periapsis.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, run the mission.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring Resources</title>

    <section>
      <title>Creating and Configuring a Spacecraft</title>

      <para>In this section we will set the spacecraft's initial epoch and
      classical orbital elements. You will need GMAT open, with the default
      mission loaded. The default mission is loaded when a new session of the
      GMAT executable is started or when the New Mission button in the Toolbar
      is clicked.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a Spacecraft</title>

        <para>Working from the GUI, you can create a new spacecraft by
        starting at the Resource Tree.</para>

        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rename the default spacecraft DefaultSC, by right-clicking
            it and selecting Rename from the drop-down menu. For this
            tutorial, name the spacecraft Sat.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Setting a Spacecraft's Epoch</title>

        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Double left-click your Sat spacecraft - this opens open the
            Spacecraft dialog box. If it is not already selected, click on the
            Orbit Tab.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Left-click the Epoch Format drop-down menu and select
            UTCGregorian. You'll see the value in the Epoch field change to
            the UTC Gregorian epoch format.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Left-click in the Epoch field, and type the desired value of
            22 Jul 2014 11:29:10.811 (or you can cut and paste from this
            text).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save the changes by clicking the Apply button at the bottom
            of the dialog box window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Setting a Spacecraft's State</title>

        <para>In this tutorial we will use the Keplerian orbital elements, and
        we will enter them with respect to Earth's MJ2000 Equator
        system.</para>

        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Continuing with the Spacecraft dialog box: change the state
            type to Keplerian by clicking the State Type drop-down menu and
            selecting "Keplerian". In Elements on the right you will see the
            GUI reconfiguring to the Keplerian representation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set the values of Elements as follows:</para>

            <para>SMA = 83474.31800000001;</para>

            <para>ECC = 0.8965199999999999;</para>

            <para>INC = 12.4606;</para>

            <para>RAAN = 112.8362;</para>

            <para>AOP = 218.9805;</para>

            <para>TA = 180</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The figure below shows how the Orbit tab of your Sat dialog
            box should look like if you set the epoch correctly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press OK button to save the changes and close the dialog box
            .</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your work to the hard disk: press the Save icon in the
            GMAT toolbar. If this is the first time you' are saving the
            mission, you'll be prompted to provide a name and location for the
            file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <figure>
          <title>Spacecraft State Setup</title>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                           fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_SpacecraftStateSetup.jpeg"
                           scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating and Configuring the Propagator</title>

      <para>Creating a new propagator involves selecting a numerical
      integrator and a force model. Let's start with the propagator:</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a Propagator</title>

        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Locate the Propagators folder in the Resource Tree.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We will use the default propagator DefaultProp. (Or, you can
            right-click the Propagators folder and select Add Propagator from
            the drop-down menu.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rename DefaultProp to LowEarthProp. (For this, right-click
            the DefaultProp, select Rename, type in the new name In the dialog
            box, and click OK.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Double left-click LowEarthProp to open its dialog box called
            PropSet. On the left side of the box you find the Integrator
            settings; we will use the default values. model.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuring the Force Model</title>

        <para>For this tutorial we will use an Earth 10x10 non-spherical
        gravity model, Jacchia-Roberts atmospheric model, and point mass
        perturbations from the Sun and Moon.</para>

        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>We continue with the PropSet-LowEarthProp dialog box. We
            will now configurets right side, which contains information on the
            force model.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Locate the Primary Bodies group on the Force Model box. In
            the Gravity group box, change both the Degree and Order to 10 by
            typing in these values.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the Drag group of Force Model, click the Atmosphere Model
            pull-down menu and select the JacchiaRoberts model.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click the Select button to the right of the Point Masses
            text box. This opens a box with a list of gravitational bodies
            from which we can select our Primary Bodies.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select "Sun" in the Available Bodies list, and add it to
            Selected Bodies on the right by clicking the right arrow found
            between the two columns.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add similarly the Moon (named Luna in GMAT) to Selected
            Bodies. The Select Bodies box should now look as the one shown
            below.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click OK to save the selected bodies and close the
            box.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <figure>
          <title>Force Model Point Mass Configuration</title>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                           fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_ForceModelPointMassConfiguration.png"
                           scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>Back in the PropSetup dialog box, make sure the box Use Solar
        Radiation Pressure is checked. You dialog box should now look as shown
        below. Click OK to save and close it..</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Force Model Configuration</title>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                           fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_ForceModelConfiguration.jpeg"
                           scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the Orbit View Plot</title>

      <para>Here we will configure the default Orbit View plot that will show
      our spacecraft Sat. We will also configure the view point, to allow us
      to see the entire orbit as we propagate the spacecraft.</para>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Output folder in Resource Tree, double-left-click the
          DefaultOrbitView to open the OrbitView dialog box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the View Object group, make sure that our spacecraft Sat is
          the only item in the Selected Spacecraft list. (If needed, use the
          procedure we used above to form the Selected Bodies list.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The orbit of Sat is highly eccentric. To view the entire orbit
          in the plot, we need to adjust the settings in the View Definition
          group. Namely, set the pull-down menu of the View Point Vector to
          Vector, and set its three numerical settings to 30000, -5000, and
          5000 respectively.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Uncheck the DrawXY Plane box in the Drawing Option
          group.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Your OrbitView dialog box should now look as shown in the
          figure below. Click OK to save and close it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>DefaultOrbitView Configuration</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_DefaultOrbitviewConfiguration.jpeg"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring the Mission Tree</title>

    <section>
      <title>Creating a Propagate Command</title>

      <para>The last step in this tutorial will be to propagate the spacecraft
      along its orbit. To this end, we need to configure a propagate command
      so that it will propagate until the spacecraft reaches the orbit
      periapis.</para>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the Mission tab to bring up the mission sequence. (The
          tab appears next to the Resources tab, near the upper left-hand
          corner of the GMAT GUI.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Double left click on the event named Propagate1. This opens
          the Propagate dialog box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure that the the field under the Propagator column
          contains LowEarthProp. (If not, right-click the first line of that
          column, and in the little Propagator box that opens, click
          LowEarthProp. Your little box should look as shown below. Hit
          OK.)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Propagate Command Propagator Select Dialog</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_PropagateCommandPropagatorSelectDialogConfiguration.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a Spacecraft</title>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Back in the Propagate1 dialog box, make sure that the
          Spacecraft List on the right contains our spacecraft Sat. (If not,
          right-click the list's top line, and select Sat in the list box that
          opens; hit OK.)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Propagate Command Space Object Select Dialog</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_PropagateCommandSpaceObjectSelectdialogConfiguration.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a Stopping Condition</title>

      <para>The only remaining thing now is to tell the propagator when to
      stop the propagation.</para>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Stopping Conditions group of our Propagate1 dialog box,
          right click the field in the Parameter column (it may now contain
          something - e.g. Sat.ElapsedSecs.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the ParameterSelectDialog box that opens, select Sat in the
          Object List on the left. (This directs GMAT to associate the
          stopping condition with the spacecraft named Sat.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Locate the Object Properties list in the middle of the box,
          scroll down and select Periapsis.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the right-pointing arrow between the Object Properties
          and Selected Value(s) columns. This forms a variable
          Sat.Earth.Periapsis and places it in the Selected Value(s) column on
          the right. (See the figure below.) Click OK to save your
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The figure below shows how your ParameterSelectDialog box will
      look like.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Propagate Command Parameter Select Dialog Configuration</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_PropagateCommandParameterSelectDialogConfiguration.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>With the propagator, spacecraft, and the stopping condition set as
      above, the Propagate1 dialog box should appear as the screen capture
      below. When finished, click OK to save the changes made to
      Propagate1.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Propagate Command Configuration</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_PropagateCommandConfiguration.jpeg"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Running the Mission</title>

    <para>With the mission now fully configured, it is time to run it and see
    the results.</para>

    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Save button in the toolbar to save your mission
        script.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Run button in the toolbar.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>You should see GMAT propagate the orbit and stop at orbit periapsis.
    The screen capture below summarizes what you should see after correctly
    completing this tutorial. You can manipulate the Orbit View plot using
    your mouse to zoom in/out and rotate the plot.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Orbit View Plot after Mission Run</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="media/img/Tut_PropSpacecraft_OrbitviewPlotAfterMissionRun.jpeg"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
