<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="IntroducingGmat" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introducing GMAT</title>


<para> GMAT is an open source trajectory design and optimization system developed by NASA and private industry. We use an open source process to
maximize tehcnology transfer and permit anyone to
develop and validate new algorithms and to enable new algorithms to quickly
transition into the high fidelity core. </para>

<para>GMAT is designed to model and optimize spacecraft trajectories in flight
regimes ranging from low Earth orbit to lunar applications, interplanetary
trajectories, and other deep space missions. The system supports constrained
and unconstrained trajectory optimization and built-in features make defining
cost and constraint functions trivial so analysts can determine how their
inclusion or exclusion effects solutions.</para>

<para>The system also contains initial value solvers (propagation) and boundary
value solvers and efficiently propagates spacecraft either singly or coupled.
GMAT's propagators naturally synchronize the epochs of multiple vehicles and shorten run times by avoiding fixed step
integration or interpolation to synchronize epochs of spacecraft.</para>

<para>A user can interact with GMAT using either a graphical user interface (GUI) or script language that has a syntax similar to
the MathWorks' MATLAB®1 system. All of the system elements can be expressed through either interface and users can
configure elements in the GUI and then view the corresponding script, or
write script and load it into GMAT.</para>

<para>Analysts model space missions in GMAT by first creating resources such
as spacecraft, propagators, and optimizers to name a few. These
resources can be configured to meet the needs of specific applications and
missions. After the resources are configured they are used in the mission
sequence to model the motion of spacecraft and simulate events in a
mission's time evolution. The mission sequence supports commands such
as Nonlinear Constraint, Minimize, Propagate, Function Calls, Inline
Math, and Script Events among others.</para>

<para>The system can display trajectories in space, plot parameters against one
another, and save parameters to files for later processing. The trajectory
and plot capabilities are fully interactive, plotting data as a mission is run
and allowing users to zoom into regions of interest. Trajectories and data
can be viewed in any coordinate system defined in GMAT, and GMAT
allows users to rotate the view and set the focus to any object in the
display. The trajectory view can be animated so users can watch the
evolution of the trajectory over time.</para>


</section>
