<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>User Guide Overview and Essential Reading</title>

  <para>The GMAT User’s Guide contains material for new and experienced users
  and is organized into the following sections:</para>

  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>Introduction to GMAT</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Getting Started</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Create Your First Mission</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>How To</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Tutorials</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Reference</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The Introduction to GMAT section contains a brief project and software
  overview, and discusses project status, licensing, and contributors.</para>

  <para>The Getting Started section of the GMAT User’s Guide describes how to
  install and start GMAT, presents an overview of the user interfaces, and
  provides information on configuring your system. We consider the user
  interface overview essential reading. <emphasis>If you read nothing else in
  the User’s Guide, at least read the “User Interfaces Overview section” as it
  will explain the basic philosophy and rules of GMAT’s user
  interfaces.</emphasis></para>

  <para>The Creating Your First Mission section walks you through step-by-step
  to create a spacecraft, a propagator, and an <guilabel>OrbitView</guilabel>
  graphical display, and then propagate the spacecraft to orbit
  perigee.</para>

  <para>The How To section of the GMAT documentation contains many articles
  that each describe a single area of functionality. The purpose is of the How
  To documentation is to show you how to use a specific feature in an analysis
  context, and these articles often start from the default mission. A How To
  doc is designed to take about five minutes to teach you a feature
  area.</para>

  <para>The Tutorials section describes how to use GMAT for end-to-end
  analysis, and tutorials start from a blank slate, rather than from a default
  mission. We’ve included a number of tutorials including a Hohmann transfer,
  Optimal Lunar Transfer, Optimal Mars Transfer, and low Earth orbit station
  keeping. Individual tutorials are designed to take between 30 minutes and
  one day to complete, and teach you how to build and configure all of the
  models and commands required to perform real-world analysis.</para>

  <para>The Reference section of the User’s Guide describes each GMAT
  interface, model and command in detail, including syntax, variable ranges
  and data types, defaults, and expected behavior.</para>
</preface>
