<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ReleaseNotesR2016a"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>GMAT R2016a Release Notes</title>

  <para>The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) version R2016a was released
  Oct. 2016. This is the first public release since Nov. 2015, and is the 10th
  release for the project. Note this will be <guilabel>the last 32 bit version
  of GMAT on Windows</guilabel> (Mac and Linux are 64 bit only).</para>

  <para>Below is a summary of key changes in this release. Please see the full
  <link
  xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=10600&amp;styleName=Html&amp;projectId=10000">R2016a
  Release Notes</link> on JIRA for a complete list.</para>

  <section>
    <title>New Features</title>

    <section>
      <title>Orbit Determination</title>

      <para>GMAT now supports orbit determination with a focus on batch
      estimation of DSN data types including range and Doppler. We’ve been
      working on navigation functionality for several releases, but this is
      the first production release containing navigation functionality. Orbit
      determination functionality has undergone a rigorous QA process
      including shadow testing in GSFC’s Flight Dynamics Facility and is
      extensively documented in tutorials and reference material. Navigation
      components include BatchEstimator, Simulator, ErrorModel,
      StatisticsAcceptFilter, StatisticsRejectFilter, TrackingDataSet, and the
      RunEstimator and RunSimulator Commands. We recommend taking the
      tutorials first then reviewing the reference material for orbit
      determination components to get started.</para>

      <para>See the <link
      linkend="Tut_Simulate_DSN_Range_and_Doppler_Data">Simulation</link> and
      <link
      linkend="Orbit_Estimation_using_DSN_Range_and_Doppler_Data">Estimation</link>
      tutorials for more information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Code 500 Ephemeris Propagator</title>

      <para>GMAT now supports a propagator that uses GSFC’s Code 500 ephemeris
      file format. The Code 500 file format is legacy format still used by
      some systems at GSFC. This functionality allows users of GSFC legacy
      systems to simulate and analyze trajectories computed in systems such as
      GTDS.</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="Propagator">Propagator</link> reference for
      more information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Write Command</title>

      <para>You can now export GMAT resources to files during the mission
      sequence execution. This is a powerful feature that allows you to save
      configurations at any point in a session for use by in later sessions or
      by other users.</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="Write">Write Command</link> reference for
      more information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>#Include Macro</title>

      <para>You can now load GMAT resources and script snippets from external
      files during the script initialization and mission execution. This is a
      powerful feature that allows you to reuse configurations across multiple
      users and/or scripts. This feature can also greatly simplify automation
      for operations and Monte-Carlo and parametric scanning that have use
      cases with a lot of common data but some data that changes from one
      execution to the next.</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="IncludeMacro">#Include</link> reference for
      more information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GetEphemStates Built-in Function</title>

      <para>Using the built-in GetEphemStates function, you can now query
      SPICE, Code-500 and STK .e ephemeris types and for a spacecraft’s
      initial epoch, initial state, final epoch and final state in any GMAT
      supported epoch formats and coordinate systems. This allows you to
      perform numerical propagation using states off of ephemiris files for
      comparison and other analysis.</para>

      <para>See the <link
      linkend="GetEphemStates_Function">GetEphemStates</link> referece for
      more information.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Improvements</title>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>You can now define the EOP file location in a script.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The system now supports finite burn parameters that report the
        thrust component data for a finite burn. The parameters include total
        thrust from all thrusters in the three coordinate directions, the
        total acceleration from all thrusters in the three coordinate
        directions, and the total mass flow rate. Furthermore, you can now
        also report individual thruster parameters such as thrust magnitude,
        Isp and mass flow rate.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT now contains built-in string manipulations functions
        sprintf, strcmp, strcat, strfind, strrep.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Several new built in math functions are implemented including a
        built-in cross product function. For manipulation of numeric data
        we've implemented mod, ceil, floor, fix. For random number generation
        we've implemented rand, randn, and SetSeed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can now model finite burns that employ multiple tanks.
        Previous versions were limited to a single tank.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT now supports generation of STK's “.e” ephemeris format in
        addition those supported previously such as CCSDS-OEM, SPK and
        Code-500 formats.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We've written over 130 pages of new, high-quality user
        documentation!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The behavior of the GUI when using large fonts has been
        improved.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compatibility Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can now override the default <guilabel>NAIFId</guilabel> on
        a <guilabel>CelestialBody</guilabel> to allow using body centers or
        barycenters as the reference for built-in celestial bodies. Previously
        this field was read-only.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Development and Tools</title>

    <section>
      <title>Developer Tools and Dependencies</title>

      <para>We updated the CMake-based build system that is used on all
      platforms. The CMake configuration is maintained by the GMAT team and
      distributed with the source code. Thanks to CMake, it is much easier to
      compile GMAT. See the <link
      xlink:href="http://gmatcentral.org/display/GW/Compiling">wiki
      documentation for details</link>. Note that old build files are no
      longer supported and are considered obsolete.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GMAT Stuff</title>

      <para>Don't forget you can purchase clothing and other items with the
      GMAT logo via ©Land's End, Inc at the <link
      xlink:href="http://ocs.landsend.com/cd/frontdoor?store_name=nasagsfc&amp;store_type=3">GSFC
      Store</link> . Once, you've chosen an item, make sure to select the GMAT
      logo!</para>

      <informalfigure>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="files/images/relnotes/r2015a/SWAG.png"
                         scale="60"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </informalfigure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Known &amp; Fixed Issues</title>

    <para>Over 100 bugs were closed in this release. See the <link
    xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=13720">"Critical
    Issues Fixed in R2016a" report</link> for a list of critical bugs and
    resolutions in R2016a. See the <link
    xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=13721">"Minor
    Issues Fixed for R2016a" report</link> for minor issues addressed in
    R2016a.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>

      <para>All known issues that affect this version of GMAT can be seen in
      the <link
      xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=13722">"Known
      Issues in R2016a" report</link> in JIRA.</para>

      <para>There are several known issues in this release that we consider to
      be significant:<informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="0.2*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">ID</entry>

                <entry align="left">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-5269">GMT-5269</link></entry>

                <entry>Atmosphere model affects propagation at GEO.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-2561">GMT-2561</link></entry>

                <entry>UTC Epoch Entry and Reporting During Leap Second is
                incorrect.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-3043">GMT-3043</link></entry>

                <entry>Inconsistent validation when creating variables that
                shadow built-in math functions</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-3289">GMT-3289</link></entry>

                <entry>First step algorithm fails for backwards propagation
                using SPK propagator</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-3350">GMT-3350</link></entry>

                <entry>Single-quote requirements are not consistent across
                objects and modes</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-3669">GMT-3669</link></entry>

                <entry>Planets not drawn during optimization in
                OrbitView</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/browse/GMT-3738">GMT-3738</link></entry>

                <entry>Cannot set standalone FuelTank, Thruster fields in
                CallMatlabFunction</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/browse/GMT-4520">GMT-4520</link></entry>

                <entry>Unrelated script line in Optimize changes results
                (causes crash)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/browse/GMT-4398">GMT-4520</link></entry>

                <entry>Coordinate System Fixed attitudes are held constant in
                SPAD SRP model during a propagation step</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
