<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ReleaseNotesR2013a"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>GMAT R2013a Release Notes</title>

  <para>The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) version R2013a was released
  in April, 2013. This is the first public release since May 23, 2012, and is
  the 6th public release for the project. R2013a is a major maintenance
  release transitioning GMAT from Beta to production quality. In this
  release:</para>

  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>End user documentation was rewritten and greatly expanded.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>11,000 script-based regression tests run nightly.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>5000 GUI-based regression tests run weekly.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Code and documentation was contributed by 11 developers from 3
      organizations.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title>Licensing</title>

    <para>GMAT is now licensed using Apache License 2.0. According to the
    <link xlink:href="http://opensource.org/proliferation-report">Open Source
    Proliferation Report</link>, Apache License 2.0 is one of the most widely
    used open source licenses thereby making GMAT compatible with more
    existing software and projects.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Major Improvements</title>

    <para>Release R2013a is a major maintenance release of GMAT. Most of our
    efforts have been devoted to improving the quality of the software and its
    documentation. This year we made a complete sweep through the system
    starting by updating engineering specifications for all features,
    identifying test gaps, writing new tests, addressing known and newly found
    bugs, and completing user documentation. Here is more detail on what we’ve
    been up to for this release.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Tutorials</title>

      <para>The GMAT user guide now contains 5 in-depth tutorials that show
      you how to use GMAT for end-to-end analysis. The tutorials are designed
      to teach you how to use GMAT in the context of performing real-world
      analysis and are intended to take between 30 minutes and several hours
      to complete. Each tutorial has a difficulty level and an approximate
      duration listed with any prerequisites in its introduction, and is
      arranged in a general order of difficulty. The simplest tutorial show
      shows you how to enter orbital initial conditions and propagate to orbit
      perigee, more advanced tutorials show how to perform finite maneuver
      targeting, Mars B-Plane targeting, and lunar flyby optimization.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reference Guide</title>

      <para>We have written a complete reference manual for GMAT for R2013a.
      The reference manual contains detailed information on all GMAT
      components. When you need detailed information on syntax or
      application-specific examples, go here.</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Brief description of the feature</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>List of related or coupled features</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Complete syntactical specification of the interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Tables with detailed options, variable ranges and data types,
          defaults, and expected behavior</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Copy-and-paste ready examples</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In the new GMAT reference manual, for each GMAT Resource (e.g.
      Spacecraft, Thruster, XYPlot) and Command (e.g. Optimize, Propagate),
      the following information is documented:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Script language syntax</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>External interfaces</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Parameter listings</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configuration files</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Command line interface</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing</title>

      <para>We have spent much of our time preparing for R2013a on testing.
      Our script and GUI-based regression test systems doubled in size in the
      last year.</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Over 6000 new system, validation, and end-to-end script-based
          tests.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>30 new end-to-end GUI tests</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>3000 new GUI system tests</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>GUI test are performed using SMARTBEAR’s Test Complete software.
      Script tests are performed using a custom MATLAB-based test system. A
      complete execution of the regression test system now takes almost four
      days of computer time.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Minor Enhancements</title>

    <para>While most of our effort has been focused on quality for this
    release, we have included some new features.</para>

    <para>ICRF is now supported for input and output of orbit state
    data</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/ReleaseNotes_R2013a_1.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Improved Earth texture map</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/ReleaseNotes_R2013a_2.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>CCSDS ephemeris files are now accessible in the output tab</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/ReleaseNotes_R2013a_3.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Improved mouse controls for interactive 3-D graphics.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Improved 3ds model support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Improved error messages</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>New axis system for asteroid surveys</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Improved system modularization by moving more features to
        plugins</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compatibility Changes</title>

    <para>Our last release, R2012a, was beta software. R2013a is mature,
    production software. We made some changes that may cause backwards
    compatibility issues with scripts written in previous beta versions.
    Examples of changes in R2013a that affect backwards compatibility with
    previous beta versions include:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Poorly named fields and/or parameters</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Missed or invalid user data validation checking</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Partially implemented functionality</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Improperly exposed internal fields and functions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configuration of some Resources in command mode</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In all cases, we modified GMAT to work correctly as specified in the
    documentation, but did not always maintain backwards compatibility with
    previous Beta versions. This was a one-time, “pull of the Band-Aid”
    approach and future releases will maintain backwards compatibility with
    R2013a or provide deprecation notifications of features that are no longer
    supported.</para>

    <para>In addition, there were some features that did not meet quality
    expectations for this release and have been turned off in the release
    package. Most of these features can be turned on for analysis purposes,
    but they are not fully tested and should be used with caution.</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Orbit designer ( cannot be turned on )</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT functions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Save command</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bulirsh-Stoer integrator</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To turn on these features, see the documentation for the GMAT
    startup file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Known &amp; Fixed Issues</title>

    <para>Over 720 bugs and issues were closed in this release. See the <link
    xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/issues/?filter=11803">"Critical
    Issues Fixed for R2013a" report</link> for a list of critical bugs and
    resolutions for R2013a. See the <link
    xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/issues/?filter=11803">"Minor
    Issues Fixed for R2013a" report</link>" for minor issues addressed in
    R2013a.</para>

    <para>All known issues that affect this version of GMAT can be seen in
    <link
    xlink:href="http://li64-187.members.linode.com:8080/secure/IssueNavigator.jspa?mode=hide&amp;requestId=11104">the
    "Known issues in R2012a" report</link> in JIRA.</para>
  </section>
</section>
