<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="OpenGLPlot"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>OpenGL Plot</title>

  <para>This tutorial was started from the default settings in the June 9,
  2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Without OpenGL Plots, you would have no way of visualizing your
    spacecraft as it traveled along its trajectory. OpenGL Plots also have a
    multitude of options that allow you to customize your view of the
    spacecraft. This makes these types of plots very useful and in most cases
    necessary to using GMAT.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Spacecraft</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Any spacecraft in your mission is available to the OpenGL
              Plot for display</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Solar System</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Sun and all of the Planets may be plotted or
              referenced in the OpenGL Plot</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If you add any Barrycenters or Libration Points, they will
              also be available for plotting and reference</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Coordinate Systems</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Both View Definition and View Up Definition may use the
              three default or user added coordinate systems</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the GUI</title>

    <para>The OpenGL Plots dialog box is quite extensive and one of the
    largest in GMAT. The below bullets outline each option available to you
    and how they all work. Refer to the screen shot below this list if you
    need a reference as you read. The box itself is split into several Group
    boxes which in turn contain up to several fields each. All of this allows
    you to not only change what is shown in the plot, but also how far away
    you view the object(s) and from what direction. There is a great deal of
    functionality beyond this as well.</para>

    <para>When you have a plot open, you may change your view using the mouse.
    Left click on the plot and move the mouse while still holding down the
    button. This will change the view point of the plot. Right click on the
    plot and again while holding the button down, move the mouse to the left
    to zoom in and to the left to zoom out.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Plot Option - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Collect data every BLANK step - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This value determines how many integration steps are
                taken between the drawing of a point on the plot. Basically,
                the greater this number, the less precise the plot is and the
                faster it will run.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update plot every BLANK cycle - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This value represents the number of integration steps
                taken between the plot's refreshing. This means that the plot
                will be redrawn with the new points from the data collected
                above.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Number of points to redraw - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This value represents how many previously collected
                plotting points will be shown. If set to 0, all points will be
                drawn. If set to some positive integer then that number of
                previous points will be drawn. This is useful when running a
                long mission when you only want the most recent information
                displayed.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show Plot - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If for any reason you do not want to display the plot,
                uncheck this box so that the object is still present in the
                mission tree but will not show up as an output when the
                mission is run.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>View Object - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Spacecraft - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This is a list of all Spacecraft in the resource tree.
                Any number of them may be added to the Selected Spacecraft
                Field.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Selected Spacecraft - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This is the list of Spacecraft that will be shown in the
                OpenGL Plot, as long as the Draw Object Check box is selected.
                These are added from those in the Spacecraft Field.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Object - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Like the Show Plot Check box does for the whole Plot,
                this box allows an object, whether it be a spacecraft or
                celestial, to be not shown in the plot if unchecked. When
                checked, the Plot will draw this object and its path.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Celestial Object - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Similar to the Spacecraft Field, this list contains all
                of the Celestial Bodies and points that are in the Solar
                System section of the resource tree. These include all of the
                Planets, the Sun, the Moon, and any points that you add under
                Special Points in the Resource tree such as Barycenters or
                Libration Points.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Selected Celestial Object - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This is a list of all Celestial Objects to be displayed
                in the plot. Any object in the Celestial Object field may be
                moved here so that you may see it.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Orbit Color - Selection</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This changes the color of the line that a celestial
                object or spacecraft will leave behind as it travels through
                space. In the case of a spacecraft in a targeting or other
                sequence that requires multiple iterations, this selection
                represents the color of its final trajectory.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Target Color - Selection</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>A spacecraft that uses multiple iterations to achieve a
                targeting, optimization, or other sort of problem, can be
                drawn through each of its runs using the color selected here.
                It is a good idea to keep this color different from the
                spacecraft's orbit color.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Drawing Option - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Wire Frame - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>When selected, the Plot will display all spacecraft and
                celestial objects as wire frame models.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Ecliptic Plane - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>When selected, the ecliptic plane, or rather, the plane
                that the Earth travels in around the Sun, will be
                displayed.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw XY Plane - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This will draw a wire mesh plane in the plane of the X
                and Y axes that the Plot is referencing as the View Definition
                Coordinate System.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Axes - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This will draw the axes of the selected coordinate
                system.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Grid - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>When selected, this option will have GMAT draw a
                longitude and latitude grid in the Plot.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Draw Sun Line - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>When checked, this option will draw a line at all times
                between the centers of the Earth and Sun.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>View Definition - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Coordinate System - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This is what coordinate system will be used in
                the</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>View Point Reference - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This is set to the center of the Plot's coordinate
                system by default but may be changed to any spacecraft or
                celestial object. It is where the View Point Vector is
                referenced from.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>View Point Vector - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The View Point Vector is where you will view the Plot
                from. It is the camera location, so to speak, with respect to
                the View Point Reference whether it be the center of the
                plot's coordinate system or defined by you above in the View
                Point Reference drop down menu.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>View Point Vector - Fields</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>These are the fields beside the View Point Vector drop
                down menu where you define the actual view point vector in the
                X, Y, Z format.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>View Scale Factor - Field</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The View Scale Factor is basically a multiplier of the
                View Point Vector. For example, if you put 5 as a value here
                then you will see the objects 5 times further away.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>View Direction - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This allows you to point the direction of view for the
                plot, the camera, toward the direction of your choosing. This
                may be towards a spacecraft or celestial object.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>View Option - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use Initial View Def. - Check Box</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use Initial View Definition is very useful when doing
                multiple runs of a mission. If left checked, your view of the
                plot will always start out the same. If you uncheck this box
                and move your view of the plot with the mouse once the mission
                has finished running, you can re-run the mission and the view
                will stay where you left it.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>View Up Definition - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Coordinate System - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The View Definition group box only gives you where your
                view of the plot is located from but does not tell GMAT which
                way is up within that view. This drop down menu allows you to
                set what coordinate system is referenced when setting the up
                direction. This will usually be the same coordinate system as
                used to define the View Direction.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Axis - Drop Down Menu</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>This tells GMAT what axis of the View Up Definition
                Coordinate System to point up in your plot.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: OpenGL Plot Default Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Resource_OpenGLPlot_OpenGLPlotDefaultDialogBox.jpeg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: OpenGL Plot Default Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Script</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script Syntax</title>

      <programlisting><code>Create OpenGLPlot DefaultOpenGL;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.SolverIterations = Current;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.Add = {DefaultSC, Earth};
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.OrbitColor = [ 255 32768 ];
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.TargetColor = [ 8421440 0 ];
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.CoordinateSystem = EarthMJ2000Eq;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewPointReference = Earth;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewPointVector = [ 0 0 30000 ];
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewDirection = Earth;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewScaleFactor = 1;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewUpCoordinateSystem = EarthMJ2000Eq;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ViewUpAxis = Z;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.CelestialPlane = Off;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.XYPlane = On;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.WireFrame = Off;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.Axes = On;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.Grid = Off;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.SunLine = Off;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.UseInitialView = On;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.DataCollectFrequency = 1;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.UpdatePlotFrequency = 50;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.NumPointsToRedraw = 0;
GMAT DefaultOpenGL.ShowPlot = true;</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Tables</title>

    <para>Fields associated with Plot Options</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>DataCollectFrequency</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 1</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt;= 1
            }</para> <para>The DataCollectFrequency field allows the user to
            define how data is collected for plotting. It is often inefficient
            to draw every ephemeris point associated with a trajectory. Often,
            drawing a smaller subset of the data still results in smooth
            trajectory plots, while executing more quickly. The
            DataCollectFrequency is an integer that represents how often to
            collect data and store for plotting. If DataCollectFrequency is
            set to 10, then Data is collected every 10 integration
            steps.</para> <para>Units: Integration Steps</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>UpdatePlotFrequency</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 50</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt;= 1
            }</para> <para>The UpdatePlotFrequency field allows the user to
            specify how often to update an OpenGL plot is updated with new
            data collected during the process of propagating spacecraft and
            running a mission. Data is collected for a plot according the
            value defined by DataCollectFrequency. An OpenGL plot is updated
            with the new data, according to the value set in
            UpdatePlotFrequency. If UpdatePlotFrequency is set to 10 and
            DataCollectFrequency is set to 2, then the plot is updated with
            new data every 20 (10*2) integration steps.</para> <para>Units:
            Integration Steps</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>NumPointsToRedraw</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt;= 0
            }</para> <para>When NumPointsToRedraw is set to zero, all
            ephemeris points are drawn. When NumPointsToRedraw is set to a
            positive integer, say 10 for example, only the last 10 collected
            data points are drawn. See DataCollectFrequency for explanation of
            how data is collected for an OpenGL plot.</para> <para>Units:
            Integration Steps</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ShowPlot</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: true</para> <para>Options: { true , false
            }</para> <para>The ShowPlot field allows the user to turn off a
            plot for a particular run, without deleting the plot object, or
            removing it from the script. If you select true, then the plot
            will be shown. If you select false, then the plot will not be
            shown.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Fields associated with Viewed Objects</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Add</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: DefaultSC, Earth</para> <para>Options: {
            SpacecraftName CelestialBodyName LibrationPointName BarycenterName
            }</para> <para>The Add subfield adds a spacecraft,celestial body,
            libration point,or barycenter to a plot. When creating a plot the
            Earth is added as a default body and may be removed by using the
            Remove command. The user can add a spacecraft, celestial body,
            libration point, or barycenter to a plot by using the name used to
            create the object. The GUI's Selected field is the equivalent of
            the script's Add field. In the event of no Add command or no
            objects in the Selected field, GMAT should run without the OpenGL
            plot and a warning message displayed in the message window. The
            following warning message is sufficient: OpenGL plot will be
            turned off. No object has been selected for plotting.</para>
            <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Remove</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: No Default</para> <para>Options: { Any
            object included in the Add list }</para> <para>The Remove subfield
            removes a spacecraft,celestial body, libration point, or
            barycenter from a plot. The user can remove any object that has
            been added to a plot by using the name used to add the
            object.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Fields associated with Drawing Options</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>WireFrame</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Off</para> <para>Options: { On , Off
            }</para> <para>When the WireFrame field is set to On, celestial
            bodies are drawn using a wireframe model. When the WireFrame field
            is set to Off, then celestial bodies are drawn using a full
            map.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>EclipticPlane</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Off</para> <para>Options: { On , Off } Note:
            Only allowed for OpenGL plots with Coordinate Systems that use the
            MJ2000Eq axis system</para> <para>The EclipticPlane field allows
            the user to tell GMAT to draw a grid representing the ecliptic
            plane in an OpenGL plot. Note, the ecliptic plane can currently
            only be drawn for plots whose coordinate system uses the MJ2000Eq
            axis system.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>XYPlane</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: On</para> <para>Options: { On , Off }</para>
            <para>The XYPlane flag allows the user to tell GMAT to draw a grid
            representing the XY-plane of the coordinate system selected under
            the CoordinateSystem field of the OpenGL plot.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Axes</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: On</para> <para>Options: { On , Off }</para>
            <para>The Axis flag allows the user to tell GMAT to draw the
            Cartesian axis system associated with the coordinate system
            selected under the CoordinateSystem field of an OpenGL
            plot.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Grid</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: On</para> <para>Options: { On , Off }</para>
            <para>The Grid flag allows the user to tell GMAT to draw a grid
            representing the longitude and latitude lines celestial bodies
            added to an OpenGL plot.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>EarthSunLines</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: On</para> <para>Options: { On , Off }</para>
            <para>The EarthSunLines allows the user to tell GMAT to draw a
            line that starts at the center of Earth and points towards the
            Sun.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>SolverIterations</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Off</para> <para>Options: { On , Off
            }</para> <para>The SolverIterations field determines whether or
            not perturbed trajectories are plotted during a solver (Targeter,
            Optimize) sequence. When SolverIterations is set to On, solver
            iterations are shown on the plot. When SolverIterations is Off,
            the solver iterations are not shown on the plot.</para> <para>
            Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Fields Associated with View Definition</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>CoordinateSystem</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: EarthMJ2000Eq</para> <para>Options: { Any
            default or user defined coordinate system }</para> <para>The
            CoordinateSystem field on an OpenGL plot allows the user to select
            which coordinate system to use to draw the plot data. A coordinate
            system is defined as an origin and an axis system, and the
            CoordinateSystem field allows the user to determine the origin and
            axis system of an OpenGL plot. See the CoordinateSystem object
            fields for information of defining different types of coordinate
            systems.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewPointReference</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Earth</para> <para>Options: { SpacecraftName
            CelestialBodyName LibrationPointName BarycenterName, or a 3-vector
            of numerical values }</para> <para> The ViewPointReference field
            is an optional field that allows the user to change the reference
            point from which ViewPointVector is measured. ViewPointReference}
            defaults to the origin of the coordinate system for the plot. A
            ViewPointReference can be any spacecraft, celestial body,
            libration point, or barycenter.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewPointVector</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: [0 0 30000]</para> <para>Options: {
            SpacecraftName CelestialBodyName LibrationPointName
            BarycenterName, or a 3-vector of numerical values }</para> <para>
            The product of ViewScaleFactor and ViewPointVector field
            determines the view point location with respect to
            ViewPointReference. ViewPointVector can be a vector, or any of the
            following objects: spacecraft,celestial body, libration point,or
            barycenter. The location of the Viewpoint in three-space is
            defined as the vector addition of ViewPointReference, and the
            vector defined by product of ViewScaleFactor and ViewPointVector
            in the coordinate system chosen by the user.</para> <para>Units:
            km or N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewScaleFactor</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 1</para> <para>Options: { Real Number &gt;=
            0 }</para> <para>The ViewScaleFactor field scales ViewPointVector
            before adding it to ViewPointReference. The ViewScaleFactor allows
            the user to back away from an object to fit in the field of
            view.</para> <para>Units: None</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewDirection</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Earth</para> <para>Options: { SpacecraftName
            CelestialBodyName LibrationPointName BarycenterName, or a 3-vector
            of numerical values }</para> <para> The ViewDirection field allows
            the user to select the direction of view in an OpenGL plot. The
            user can specify the view direction by choosing an object to point
            at such as a spacecraft,celestial body, libration point,or
            barycenter. Alternatively, the user can specify a vector of the
            form [x y z]. If the user specification of ViewDirection,
            ViewPointReference, and ViewPointVector, results in a zero vector,
            GMAT uses [0 0 10000] for ViewDirection.</para> <para>Units: km or
            N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Fields Associated with View Options</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>UseInitialView</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: On</para> <para>Options: { On , Off }</para>
            <para>The UseInitialView field allows the user to control the view
            of an OpenGL plot between multiple runs of a mission sequence. The
            first time a specific OpenGL plot is created, GMAT will
            automatically use the view as defined by the fields associated
            with View Definition, View Up Direction, and Field of View.
            However, if the user changes the view using the mouse, GMAT will
            retain this view upon rerunning the mission if UseInitialView is
            set to false. If UseInitialView is set to true, the view for an
            OpenGL plot will be returned to the view defined by the initial
            settings.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Fields Associated with View Up Definition</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewUpCoordinate System</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: EarthMJ2000Eq</para> <para>Options: { Any
            default or user defined coordinate system }</para> <para>The
            ViewUpCoordinateSystem and ViewUpAxis fields are used to determine
            which direction appears as up in an OpenGL plot and together with
            the fields associated the the View Direction, uniquely define the
            view. The fields associated with the View Definition allow the
            user to define the point of view in 3-space, and the direction of
            the line of sight. However, this information alone is not enough
            to uniquely define the view. We also must provide how the view is
            oriented about the line of sight. This is accomplished by defining
            what direction should appear as the up direction in the plot and
            is configured using the ViewUpCoordinateSystem field and the
            ViewUpAxis field. The ViewUpCoordinateSystem allows the user to
            select a coordinate system to define the up direction. Most of the
            time this system will be the same as the coordinate system chosen
            under the CoordinateSystem field.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ViewUpAxis</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Z</para> <para>Options: { X , -X , Y , -Y ,
            Z , -Z }</para> <para>The ViewUpAxis allows the user to define
            which axis of the ViewUpCoordinateSystem that will appear as the
            up direction in an OpenGL plot. See the comments under
            ViewUpCoordinateSystem for more details of fields used to
            determine the up direction in an OpenGL plot.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
