<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry version="5.0"
          xml:id="MATLABInterface"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <indexterm>
    <primary>MATLABInterface</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>MATLABInterface</refentrytitle>

    <refmiscinfo class="source">GMAT</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="version">2012a</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="manual">Resources</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>MATLABInterface</refname>

    <refpurpose>
      Interface to MATLAB system
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsection>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>
      The MATLAB interface provides a link to the Mathworks MATLAB environment, allowing GMAT to run MATLAB functions as if they were native functions in the GMAT script language.
    </para>

    <para>
      The interface cannot be controlled directly through the script language, though it can be in the GMAT GUI. Instead, GMAT starts the interface automatically when it calls a MATLAB function.
    </para>

    <para>
      For details on declaring a MATLAB function, see the <guilabel>MatlabFunction</guilabel> reference. For details on calling a function and passing data, see the <guilabel>MATLAB Function Call</guilabel> reference.
    </para>

    <para>
      <phrase role="ref_seealso">See Also</phrase>: <xref
        linkend="MatlabFunction"/>, <xref linkend="CallMatlabFunction"/>
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>GUI</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/Resource_MATLABInterface_GUI.png"
                     scalefit="1"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      The MATLAB interface provides an icon in the Interfaces folder in the Resources tree that can be used to control the interface. 
      Right-clicking the icon shows two options: <guilabel>Open</guilabel> and <guilabel>Close</guilabel>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>Open</guilabel> menu item causes GMAT to open a connection to the MATLAB Engine, which in turns displays a MATLAB command window in the background. 
      This connection is then used for all communication between GMAT and MATLAB until the connection is closed. Only one connection can be open at a time.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>Close</guilabel> menu item causes GMAT to close any open connection to the MATLAB Engine. If no connection is open, it has no effect.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Remarks</title>

    <refsection>
      <title>Interface Setup</title>

      <para>
        The following conditions must be true for GMAT to successfully initiate communication with MATLAB. All conditions must be true for the same instance of MATLAB.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A compatible, licensed version of MATLAB must be installed on the 
            same machine on which GMAT is running. GMAT officially supports the current version of MATLAB at the time of release, though versions R2006b and newer have been known to work.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The architecture (32-bit or 64-bit) of GMAT and the installed version of MATLAB must match.
            For example, the 32-bit version of GMAT is compatible only with the 32-bit version of MATLAB.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Windows:
            
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The following path (where &lt;MATLAB&gt; is the path to the installed version of MATLAB) must
                  be present in the Path environment variable. For some older versions of MATLAB, this path must be present before the default Windows paths.
                  
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        &lt;MATLAB&gt;\bin\win32 (or win64 for use with 64-bit versions of GMAT)
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>
                  MATLAB must be registered as a COM server. This is done automatically by the MATLAB installer. To do it manually, open an elevated command window and run the command:
                  matlab -regserver
                  Make sure the proper instance of MATLAB is being run by this command.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Mac OS X:
            
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The MATLABFORGMAT environment variable must exist and contain the full path to the MATLAB application bundle (e.g. /Applications/MATLAB_R2012b/MATLAB_R2012b.app).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Linux:
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </refsection>
    
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>MATLAB Engine Connection</title>

    <warning>
      <para>
        Caution: GMAT does not close the MATLAB Command Window it creates after a run has completed. 
        This allows manual inspection of the MATLAB workspace, but it can lead to confusing behavior if MATLAB functions or paths are changed and rerun in the same window.
      </para>

      <para>
        We recommend closing the MATLAB Command Window by right-clicking Matlab in the Resources tree and clicking Close between each run if you are actively editing the script.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
      When GMAT runs a mission that contains a MATLAB function call,
      it opens a connection to the MATLAB engine before it makes the function call. It then reuses this connection for the rest of the GMAT session.
    </para>

    <para>
      The MATLAB Engine can be controlled manually through the <guilabel>Open</guilabel> and <guilabel>Close</guilabel> 
      options available by right-clicking the <guilabel>Matlab</guilabel> item in the Resources tree.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      (Same examples as MatlabFunction)
    </para>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
