<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="Barycenter"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Barycenter</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>A barycenter is the center of mass of two or more objects and is
    located under the Solar System folder in the resource tree. The Barycenter
    object allows you to create a special point that can be used as a
    reference point or a point to be used for the plots.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Coordinate Systems</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Interacts with the barycenter object selecting it as the
              origin of the coordinate system or as a primary or secondary
              point for defining the axes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>OpenGL Plot</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>It can be selected as a celestial object to be drawn onto
              the plot, a View Point Reference, or the View Direction within
              the dialog box.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the GUI</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Available Bodies</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Under this column are the list of celestial bodies that can
            be combined to make a barycenter or the center of mass. This list
            includes: Sun, Mercury, Venus, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune,
            Pluto, Earth, and Luna. As some of these bodies are added to
            Bodies Selected, they are automatically removed from the list of
            available bodies. When a body is selected in the Available Bodies
            column, the right arrow can be clicked to move it to the Bodies
            Selected column.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bodies Selected</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The barycenter is calculated using the bodies that are under
            this column. This column should contain two or more bodies for
            this object to be effective, unless a body's center of mass is
            significantly off center. By default, Earth and Luna start in this
            column. If an object in this column is selected and the left arrow
            is clicked, that object is cleared from the Body Selected column
            and moved back to the list of potential bodies used in the
            Available Bodies column. If the double left arrow is clicked, all
            of the bodies in the Bodies Selected column are moved to the
            Bodies Selected column.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Barycenter Object Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="files/images/Resource_Barycenter_BarycenterObjectDialogBox.jpeg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Barycenter Object Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Script</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script Syntax</title>

      <programlisting><code>Create Barycenter EarthMoonBary;
GMAT EarthMoonBary.BodyNames = {Earth, Luna};</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>&lt;BodyNames&gt;</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Earth, Luna.</para> <para>Options: { Sun,
            Mercury, Venus, Earth, Luna, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus,
            Neptune, Pluto. (At least one body must be selected!) }</para>
            <para>The BodyNames field is a list that contains the bodies used
            to define a barycenter. In a script, the list must be surrounded
            by curly braces. (i.e. BaryCenterName.BodyNames = { Earth, Luna
            })</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
