<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="Propagator"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Propagator</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>In GMAT, a Propagator is a combination of an integrator and a force
    model. Hence, a Propagator contains a physical model of the space
    environment that is used to model the motion of a spacecraft as it moves
    forwards or backwards in time (VOP formulation is not currently
    supported). You configure a Propagator by selecting among different
    numerical integrators and environment models to create a Propagator
    appropriate to the flight regime of your spacecraft during its mission.
    GMAT supports numerous numerical integrators as well as Force Models like
    point mass and non-spherical gravity, atmospheric drag (Earth), and solar
    radiation pressure.</para>

    <para>To propagate spacecraft in GMAT, you first create and configure a
    Propagator object in the script or in the Resource Tree. Then, in the
    mission sequence, you create a Propagate command, the topic of another
    section, and select among previously existing Propagators and Spacecraft.
    Hence, a Propagator is different from a Propagate command: A Propagator is
    a resource and is found in the GUI under the resource tree, and a
    Propagate Event is configured under the Mission Tree and is how you
    instruct GMAT to propagate spacecraft.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interfaces</title>

    <para>The Propagator dialog box is illustrated below and contains two
    group boxes: the Integrator group and the Force Model group. This section
    discusses the items in each group on the Propagate Panel. It will present
    how to configure a propagator and discuss all possible user settable
    fields in detail.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Integrator Group</title>

      <para>The Integrator group allows you to select and configure a
      numerical integrator appropriate to your application. You select the
      type of numerical integrator in the -+Type+- pull-down menu. After
      selecting the integrator type, the fields below the -+Type+- pull-down
      menu dynamically configure to allow you to set relevant parameters for
      the selected integrator type. All integrators except for
      Adams-Bashforth-Moulton (ABM) are configured using the same fields. The
      ABM integrator has the following additional fields:
      -+MinIntegrationerror+- and -+NomIntegrationerror+-.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Force Model Group</title>

      <para>The Force Model group allows you to configure a force model
      appropriate to the flight regime of your application. The central body
      of propagation and error control method are also defined here. On a
      Propagator, GMAT classifies all celestial bodies into two mutually
      exclusive categories: Primary Bodies, and Point Masses. Primary bodies
      can have a complex force model that includes non-spherical gravity,
      drag, and magnetic field. Point mass bodies only have a point-mass
      gravitational force.</para>

      <para>You can add a Primary Body by clicking the Select button in the
      Primary Bodies group box. Once you have added a Primary Body (or
      mulitiple bodies in future versions), the pull down menu allows you to
      configure the force model for each Primary Body. The text box, next to
      the Select button contains a list of all Primary Bodies so you can see
      which bodies are being treated with complex force models. In future
      versions, GMAT will support multiple primary bodies on a propagator
      allowing you to use a non-spherical gravity model for the Earth and Moon
      simultaneously.</para>

      <para>Configuring certain fields in the Force Model group affects the
      availability of other fields. For example, if you remove all bodies from
      the Primary Bodies list, the Gravity Field, Atmosphere Model, and
      Magnetic Field groups are disabled. Similarly, in the Gravity Field
      group, the search button and the Model File field are only active if
      "Other" is selected in the -+Type+- pull-down. In the Atmosphere Model
      group, the Setup button is only active when -+MSISE90+- or
      -+JacchiaRoberts+- are selected in the -+Type+- pull-down.</para>

      <para>GMAT allows you to define Solar flux properties if you select
      either the -+MSISE90+- or -+JacchiaRoberts+- atmosphere models. By
      selecting one of these models in the -+Type+- pull-down menu in the
      Atmosphere Model group, the Setup button is enabled. Clicking on the
      Setup button brings up the panel illustrated below. Here you can input
      Solar flux values. GMAT does not currently support flux files though
      future versions will.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <info>
          <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Propagator Object
          Dialog Box</title>
        </info>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" align="center"
                       fileref="files/images/Resource_Prop_Default.jpeg"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Propagator Object
            Dialog Box</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <programlisting><code>Create ForceModel DefaultProp_ForceModel;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.CentralBody = Earth;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.PrimaryBodies = {Earth};
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.Drag = None;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.SRP = Off;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.ErrorControl = RSSStep;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.GravityField.Earth.Degree = 4;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.GravityField.Earth.Order = 4;
GMAT DefaultProp_ForceModel.GravityField.Earth.PotentialFile = 'JGM2.cof';

Create Propagator DefaultProp;
GMAT DefaultProp.FM = DefaultProp_ForceModel;
GMAT DefaultProp.Type = RungeKutta89;
GMAT DefaultProp.InitialStepSize = 60;
GMAT DefaultProp.Accuracy = 9.999999999999999e-012;
GMAT DefaultProp.MinStep = 0.001;
GMAT DefaultProp.MaxStep = 2700;
GMAT DefaultProp.MaxStepAttempts = 50;</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <section>
      <title>Force Model Group Box Fields</title>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>ErrorControl</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: RSSStep</para> <para>Options: { RSSStep,
              RSSState, LargestState, LargestStep }</para> <para>The
              ErrorControl field allows you to choose how a Propagator
              measures the error in an integration step. The algorithm
              selected in the ErrorControl field is used to determine the
              error in the current step, and this error is compared to the
              value set in the Accuracy field to determine if the step has an
              acceptable error or needs to be improved. </para> <para>All
              error measurements are relative error, however, the reference
              for the relative error changes depending upon the selection of
              ErrorControl. RSSStep is the Root Sum Square (RSS) relative
              error measured with respect to the current step. RSSState is the
              (RSS) relative error measured with respect to the current state.
              LargestStep is the state vector component with the largest
              relative error measured with respect to the current step.
              LargestState is the state vector component with the largest
              relative error measured with respect to the current state. For a
              more detailed discussion see the GMAT Mathematical
              Specification. Units: N/A.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>CentralBody</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: Earth</para> <para>Options: { Sun,
              Mercury, Venus, Earth, Luna, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus,
              Neptune, Pluto }</para> <para>The CentralBody field allows the
              user to select the origin for the propagation. All propagation
              occurs in the FK5 axes system, about the CentralBody chosen by
              the user. The CentralBody must be a gravitational body and so
              cannot be a LibrationPoint or other special point. Units:
              N/A.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>PrimaryBodies</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: Earth</para> <para>Options: { Sun,
              Mercury, Venus, Earth, Luna, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus,
              Neptune, Pluto }</para> <para>The PrimaryBodies field is a list
              of all celestial bodies that are to be modelled with a force
              model more complex than point mass gravity. Lists are surrounded
              by curly braces. For each PrimaryBody, the user can choose a
              drag, magnetic field, and aspherical gravity model. There is a
              coupling between the PrimaryBodies filed and the PointMasses
              field. A primary body can be any planet or moon not included in
              the PointMasses field. Units: N/A. </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Gravity.PrimaryBody.PotentialFile</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: JGM2</para> <para>Options:
              {CentralBody-based models, Other. See Comments }</para>
              <para>This field allows the user to define the source for the
              non-spherical gravity coefficients for a primary body. If a
              gravity file is located in the Primary Body's potential path as
              defined in the startup file, you only need to specify the model
              name and not the entire path. For example, if the JGM2
              coefficients file is contained in the directory defined in the
              startup file by the line EARTH\_POT\_PATH, then you only need to
              specify the model name JGM2. If the model is not contained in
              the body's potential path, you must supply the entire path as
              well as the file name. If GMAT does not successfully find the
              file requested, it uses the default gravity model as defined in
              the startup file. From the GUI, only models for Earth appear if
              Earth is the active primary body. This is to avoid allowing the
              user to select a lunar potential model for the Earth. If the
              Other option is selected the user has the ability of selecting a
              gravity model file on their local computer. Units: None.
              </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Gravity.PrimaryBody.Degree</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 4</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt;= 0
              and &lt; the maximum specified by the model, Order &lt;=
              Degree}</para> <para>This field allows the user to select the
              the degree, or number of zonal terms, in the non-spherical
              gravity model. Ex. Gravity.Earth.Degree = 2 tells GMAT to use
              only the J2 zonal term for the Earth. The value for Degree must
              be less than the maximum degree specified by the Model. Units:
              None.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Gravity.PrimaryBody.Order</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 4</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt;= 0
              and &lt; the maximum specified by the model, Order &lt;=
              Degree}</para> <para>This field allows the user to select the
              the order, or number of tesseral terms, in the non-spherical
              gravity model. Ex. Gravity.Earth.Order = 2 tells GMAT to use 2
              tesseral terms. Note: Order must be greater than or equal to
              Degree. Units: None.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Drag</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: None.</para> <para>Options: { None,
              JacchiaRoberts, MSISE90, Exponential }</para> <para>The Drag
              field allows a user to specify a drag model. Currently, only one
              drag model can be chosen for a particular propagator and only
              Earth models are available. Units: N/A. Note: This field will be
              deprecated in future versions of GMAT. Currently, the Drag field
              and the Drag.AtmosphereModel field must be set to the same
              value.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Drag.AtmosphereModel</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: None.</para> <para>Options: { None,
              JacchiaRoberts, MSISE90, Exponential }</para> <para>The
              Drag.AtmosphereModel field allows a user to specify a drag
              model. Currently, only one drag model can be chosen for a
              particular propagator and only Earth models are available.
              Units: N/A.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Drag.F107</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 150</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
              &gt;= 0 }</para> <para>The Drag.F107 field allows you to set the
              F<subscript>10.7</subscript> solar flux value used in computing
              atmospheric density. F<subscript>10.7</subscript> is the solar
              radiation at a wavelength of 10.7 cm. Units:
              W/m<superscript>2</superscript>/Hz</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Drag.F107A</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 150</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
              &gt;= 0 }</para> <para>The Drag.F107A field allows you to set
              the average F<subscript>10.7</subscript> value.
              F<subscript>10.7</subscript> is the average of
              F<subscript>10.7</subscript> over one month. Units:
              W/m<superscript>2</superscript>/Hz</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Drag.MagneticIndex</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 3</para> <para>Options: { 0 &lt;= Real
              Number &lt;= 9 }</para> <para>The Drag.MagneticIndex index field
              allows you to set the k<subscript>p</subscript> value for use in
              atmospheric density calculations. k<subscript>p</subscript> is a
              planetary 3-hour-average, geomagnetic index that measures
              magnetic effects of solar radiation. Units: None.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>PointMasses</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: None</para> <para>Options: { Sun, Mercury,
              Venus, Earth, Luna, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune,
              Pluto }</para> <para>A PointMass is a planet or moon that is
              modelled by a point source located at its center of gravity. A
              PointMass body can be any planet or moon not included in the
              PrimaryBodies field. Units: N/A.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SRP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: Off</para> <para>Options: { On, Off
              }</para> <para>The SRP field allows the user to include the
              force due to solar radiation pressure in the total sum of
              forces. Units: N/A.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Integrator Group Box Fields</title>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para> Type</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: RungeKutta89</para> <para>Options: {
              RungeKutta89, RungeKutta68, RungeKutta56, PrinceDormand45,
              PrinceDormand78, BulirschStoer, AdamsBashforthMoulton }</para>
              <para>The Type field is used to set the type of numerical
              integrator.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>InitialStepSize</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 60 (sec)</para> <para>Options: { Real
              Number }</para> <para>The InitialStepSize is the size of the
              first attempted step by the integrator. If the step defined by
              InitialStepSize does not satisfy Accuracy, the integrator adapts
              the step according an algorithm defined in the mathematical
              specifications document to find an acceptable first step that
              meets the user's requested.</para> <para>Units:
              seconds</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Accuracy</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 1e-11</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
              &gt;= 0 }</para> <para>The Accuracy field is used to set the
              desired accuracy for an integration step. When you set a value
              for Accuracy, GMAT uses the method selected in ErrorControl
              field on the Force Model, to determine a metric of the accuracy.
              For each step, the integrator ensures that the accuracy, as
              calculated using the method defined by ErrorControl, is less
              than the limit defined by Accuracy. If an integrator exceeds
              MaxStepAttempts trying to meet the requested accuracy, and error
              message is thrown and propagation stops.</para> <para>Units:
              N/A</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>MinStep</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: .001 (sec)</para> <para>Options: { Real
              Number &gt; 0, MinStep &lt;= MaxStep }</para> <para>The MinStep
              field is used to set the minimum allowable step size.</para>
              <para>Units: seconds</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>MaxStep</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 2700.0 (sec.)</para> <para>Options: { Real
              Number &gt; 0, MinStep &lt;= MaxStep }</para> <para>The MaxStep
              field is used to set the maximum allowable step size.</para>
              <para>Units: seconds</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>MaxStepAttempts</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 50</para> <para>Options: { Integer &gt; 0
              }</para> <para>The MaxStepAttempts field allows the user to set
              the number of attempts the integrator takes to meet the
              tolerance defined by Accuracy.</para> <para>Units:
              None</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>Fields associated only with Adams-Bashforth-Moulton
      Integrator</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>MinIntegrationerror</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 1.0e-13</para> <para>Options: { Real
              Number &gt; 0, MinIntegrationerror &lt; NomIntegrationerror &lt;
              Accuracy }</para> <para>The MinIntegrationerror field is used by
              the ABM integrator (and other predictor-corrector integrators
              when implemented) as the desired integration error to be
              obtained when the step size is changed. Predictor-Corrector
              integrators adapt step size when the obtained integration error
              falls outside of the range of acceptable steps, as determined by
              the bounds set by the MinIntegrationerror and Accuracy fields.
              The integrator then applies an internal calculation to recompute
              the step size, attempting to hit the NomIntegrationerror, and
              restarts the integrator.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NomIntegrationerror</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Default: 1.0e-11</para> <para>Options: { Real
              Number &gt; 0, MinIntegrationerror , NomIntegrationerror ,
              Accuracy }</para> <para>The NomIntegrationerror field is used by
              the ABM integrator (and other predictor-corrector integrators
              when implemented) as the desired integration error to be
              obtained when the step size is changed. Predictor-Corrector
              integrators adapt step size when the obtained integration error
              falls outside of the range of acceptable steps, as determined by
              the bounds set by the MinIntegrationerror and Accuracy fields.
              The integrator then applies an internal calculation to recompute
              the step size, attempting to hit the NomIntegrationerror, and
              restarts the integrator.</para> <para>Units: N/A</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Object and Command Interactions</title>

    <para>A Propagator Requires Other Objects/Commands of Type: Force Model
    (Script Only). (Note: There are slight differences in how you configure a
    Propagator in the script and GUI and we refer you to the script example
    shown in the script section for details. Effort has been made to reduce
    any difference between the script and GUI.)</para>
  </section>
</section>
