<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ImpulsiveBurn"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Impulsive Burn</title>

  <para>This tutorial was started from the default settings in the June 9,
  2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The impulsive burn object in GMAT allows the spacecraft to undergo
    an instantaneous ?V in up to three dimensions as opposed to a finite burn
    which is not instantaneous. The user can configure the burn by defining
    its origin, type of axes, vector format, and magnitude of the vectors.
    Depending on the mission, it will be simpler to use one axes or vector
    format over the other.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Possible Coupling with Other Objects</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Spacecraft</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Must be created in order to apply any burn. The purpose of
              the impulsive burn is to instantaneously propel the spacecraft
              to either target or optimize a goal during its mission.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maneuver command</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Must be created to call the burn into the mission sequence
              because without a maneuver, the spacecraft simply propagates
              around a specified trajectory. If there are several burns that
              exist, in the Maneuver dialog box the user can choose which burn
              to utilize for that part of the mission sequence. In addition, a
              Propagate command must follow the maneuver to allow the
              trajectory to unfold after a burn has been applied.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Vary command</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Required a burn to be specified in the Variable Setup
              group box. The purpose of the Vary command is to apply a burn in
              order to change a parameter of the spacecraft's
              trajectory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the GUI</title>

    <para>The Impulsive Burn dialog box contains three drop down menus and one
    group box to set the magnitude of the burn in three dimensions. Setting
    the first three menus to any property installs a tentative coordinate
    system about that object without having to add one under the Coordinate
    Systems folder in the resource tree.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Origin - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The parameter for the origin can be any celestial body or
            other spacecraft. Selecting the spacecraft that is experiencing
            the burn will return a null set since the position would always be
            zero in all directions.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Axes - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Depending on the mission, two types of axes are available.
            The MJ2000Eq option applies a Cartesian approach where the burn is
            specified in an XYZ format, while the VNB option utilizes the burn
            as specified in the velocity, normal, and binormal directions, the
            velocity direction being positive X. Notice when the axes type is
            changed, the vector magnitude fields will change to correspond
            with it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Vector Format - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>This field only supplies a Cartesian option for the vector
            to maintain it in an XYZ or VNB format.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Vector - Group Box</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>This group box allows magnitudes to be entered for each of
            the three dimensions of the burn. As mentioned above, by changing
            the Axes field from MJ2000Eq to VNB, the group box will change
            accordingly to match up with the axes chosen. Also, the VNB axes
            requires additional information at the start of the mission. The
            main issue with VNB Axes is that it is impossible to locate a
            spacecraft with just that information. Some of the angles (RAAN,
            azimuth, TA, etc.) must be known to adequately specify a location,
            but the system can be advantageous if dealing with a spinning axis
            on the spacecraft, for example.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Impulsive Burn Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="files/images/Resource_ImpulsiveBurn_ImpulsiveBurnDialogBox.jpeg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Impulsive Burn Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Script</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script Syntax</title>

      <programlisting><code>Create ImpulsiveBurn ImpulsiveBurn1;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.Origin = Earth;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.Axes = VNB;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.VectorFormat = Cartesian;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.Element1 = 0;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.Element2 = 0;
GMAT ImpulsiveBurn1.Element3 = 0;</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Origin</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Earth.</para> <para>Options: { Any celestial
            body }</para> <para>Together the Origin and Axes fields describe
            the coordinate system in which a maneuver is applied. The Origin
            field determines the origin of the maneuver coordinatesystem. The
            ability to define the coordinate system locally avoids having to
            create many coordinate systems, associated with specific
            spacecraft, in order to perform finite maneuvers for multiple
            spacecraft.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Axes</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: VNB.</para> <para>Options: { VNB,MJ2000Eq
            }</para> <para>The Axes field, together with the Origin field,
            describethe coordinate system in which an impulsive maneuver is
            applied. If VNB is chosen for Axes, a local coordinate system is
            created such that the x-axis points in the velocity direction of
            thespacecraft, with respect to the point defined by Origin, the
            y-axis points in the normal direction of the spacecraft with
            respect to Origin, and the z-axis completes the right-handed
            set.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>VectorFormat</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Cartesian.</para> <para>Options: { Cartesian
            }</para> <para>The VectorFormat field allows the user to define
            the format of the maneuver vector.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Element1</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
            }</para> <para>The Element1 field allows the user to define the
            first element of the impulsive maneuver vector. Element1 is X if
            VectorFormat is Cartesian. Units: km/sec.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Element2</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
            }</para> <para>The Element2 field allows the user to define the
            second element of the impulsive maneuver vector. Element2 is Y if
            VectorFormat is Cartesian.</para> <para>Units:
            km/sec.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Element3</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
            }</para> <para>The Element3 field allows the user to define the
            third element of the impulsive maneuver vector. Element3 is Z if
            VectorFormat is Cartesian.</para> <para>Units:
            km/sec.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
