<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="DifferentialCorrector"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>DifferentialCorrector</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>A differential corrector is a numerical solver for solving two-point
    boundary value problems. The DC in GMAT uses a simple shooting method
    where the derivatives are determined using finite differencing. In the
    mission sequence, you use the differential corrector object in a Target
    sequence to solve two-point value problems. For example, differential
    correctors are often used to determine the maneuver components required to
    achieve desired orbital conditions, say, B-plane conditions at a planetary
    flyby.</para>

    <para>You must create and configure a differential corrector object
    according to your application by setting numerical properties of the
    solver such as tolerance and maximum iterations. You can also select among
    different output options that show increasing levels of information for
    each differential corrector iteration.</para>

    <para>The allowable settings for a differential corrector are shown in the
    GUI screen shots and reference table below. You can learn more about how
    to use a DC in a targeting sequence by reading the help files for Target,
    Vary, and Achieve.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interfaces</title>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Differential
        Corrector Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="files/images/Resource_DifferentialCorrector_Default.bmp"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Differential
          Corrector Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <programlisting><code>Create DifferentialCorrector DefaultDC;
GMAT DefaultDC.ShowProgress = true;
GMAT DefaultDC.ReportStyle = 'Normal';
GMAT DefaultDC.TargeterTextFile = 'DifferentialCorrectorDefaultDC.data';
GMAT DefaultDC.MaximumIterations = 25;
GMAT DefaultDC.UseCentralDifferences = false;</code></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>MaximumIterations</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 25</para> <para>Options: Integer &gt;=
            1</para> <para>The MaximumIterations field allows the user to set
            the maximum number of iterations the differential corrector is
            allowed during the attempt to find a solution. If the maximum
            iterations is reached, GMAT exits the target loop and continues to
            the next command in the mission sequence. In this case, the
            objects retain their states as of the last nominal pass through
            the targeting loop.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>DerivativeMethod</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: ForwardDifference</para> <para>Options:
            [ForwardDifference, BackwardDifference, CentralDifference]</para>
            <para>The DerivativeMethod field allows the user to choose between
            one-sided and central differencing for numerically determining the
            Jacobian matrix.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ShowProgress</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: true.</para> <para>Options: [true,
            false]</para> <para>When the ShowProgress field is set to true,
            then data illustrating the progress of the differential correction
            process are written to the message window. The message window is
            updated with information on the current control variable values
            and the contraint variances for both on perturbation and iteration
            passes. When the ShowProgress field is set to false, no
            information on the progress of the differential correction process
            is displayed.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ReportStyle</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Normal .</para> <para>Options: [Normal,
            Concise, Verbose, Debug]:</para> <para>The ReportStyle field
            allows the user to control the amount and type of information
            written to the file defined in the ReportFile field. Currently,
            the Normal and Concise options contain the same information: the
            Jacobian, the inverse of the Jacobian, the current values of the
            control variables, and achieved and desired values of the
            constraints. Verbose contains values of the perturbation variables
            in addition to the data for Normal and Concise. Debug contains
            detailed script snippets at each iteration for objects who have
            control variables.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>ReportFile</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: DifferentialCorrectorDCName.</para>
            <para>Options: [Filename consistent with OS]</para> <para>The
            ReportFile field allows the user to specify the path and file name
            for the differential correction report.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Object and Command Interactions</title>

    <para>The Differential Corrector does not interact directly with any
    resource objects.</para>

    <para>The Differential Corrector is used in the following mission sequence
    commands:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Target</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Vary</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Achieve</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
