<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="FiniteBurn"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Finite Burn</title>

  <para>This was created using the July 2, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The Finite Burn object is used when a continuous propulsion is
    desired. Impulsive burns happen instantaneously and through a Maneuver
    command, while finite burns occur until the End Finite Burn command is
    reached in the mission sequence and are typically coupled with Propagate
    commands.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Origin</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Earth.</para> <para>Options: { Any celestial
            body, libration point, or barycenter }</para> <para>Together the
            Origin and Axes fields describe the coordinate system in which a
            maneuver is applied. The Origin field determines the origin of the
            maneuver coordinate system. The ability to define the coordinate
            system locally avoids having to create many coordinate systems,
            associated with specific spacecraft, in order to perform finite
            maneuvers for multiple spacecraft.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Axes</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: VNB.</para> <para>Options: { VNB, MJ2000Eq
            }</para> <para>The Axes field, together with the Origin field,
            describe the coordinate system in which a finite maneuver is
            applied. If VNB is chosen for Axes, a local coordinate system is
            created such that the x-axis points in the velocity direction of
            the spacecraft, with respect to the point defined by Origin, the
            y-axis points in the normal direction of the spacecraft with
            respect to Origin, and the z-axis completes the right-handed
            set.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Thrusters</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: No Default.</para> <para>Options: { Any
            thruster created by user }</para> <para>The Thrusters field allows
            the selection of which thrusters to use when applying a finite
            maneuver. The user can select more than one thruster, from the
            list of thrusters previously created, by including all thrusters
            in curly braces. An example is MyFiniteBurn.Thrusters =
            Thruster1,Thruster2,Thruster3.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>BurnScaleFactor</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 1.0.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number
            }</para> <para>The BurnScaleFactor is used to scale the total
            acceleration before adding the acceleration due to a finite burn
            into the sum of the accelerations of a spacecraft. The scaling is
            performed by taking the sum of the accelerations applied by all
            thrusters specified under the Thrusters field, and multiplying the
            total thrust by BurnScaleFactor.</para> <para>Units:
            None.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Finite Burn Object
        Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Resource_FiniteBurn_Default.jpeg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Finite Burn Object
          Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <programlisting><code>Create FiniteBurn FiniteBurn1;
GMAT FiniteBurn1.Origin = Earth;
GMAT FiniteBurn1.Axes = VNB;
GMAT FiniteBurn1.BurnScaleFactor = 1;</code></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Objects and Commands Interactions</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Spacecraft</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A spacecraft must be created in order to apply any
            burn.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Thruster</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Any thruster created in the resource tree can be
            incorporated into a finite burn to be used on the
            spacecraft.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Begin and End Finite Burn command</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>After a finite burn is created, to apply it to the mission
            sequence, a Begin and End Finite Burn command must be appended to
            the mission tree.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
