<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry version="5.0" xml:id="MatlabInterface"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <indexterm>
    <primary>MATLAB Interface</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>MATLAB Interface</refentrytitle>

    <refmiscinfo class="source">GMAT</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="manual">Resources</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>MATLAB Interface</refname>

    <refpurpose>Interface to MATLAB system</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsection>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>The MATLAB interface provides a link to the Mathworks MATLAB
    environment, allowing GMAT to run MATLAB functions as if they were native
    functions in the GMAT script language.</para>

    <para>The interface cannot be controlled directly through the script
    language, though it can be in the GMAT GUI. Instead, GMAT starts the
    interface automatically when it calls a MATLAB function.</para>

    <para>There are two GMAT components that provide user access to the
    interface. For details on declaring a MATLAB function, see the
    <guilabel><xref linkend="MatlabFunction"/></guilabel> reference. For
    details on calling a function and passing data, see the <guilabel><xref
    linkend="CallMatlabFunction"/></guilabel> reference.</para>

    <para><phrase role="ref_seealso">See Also</phrase>: <xref
    linkend="CallMatlabFunction"/>, <xref linkend="MatlabFunction"/></para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>GUI</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/System_MatlabInterface_ResourcesTree.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The MATLAB interface provides an icon in the
    <guilabel>Interfaces</guilabel> folder in the Resources tree that can be
    used to control the interface. Right-clicking the icon shows two options:
    <guilabel>Open</guilabel> and <guilabel>Close</guilabel>.</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Open</guilabel> menu item causes GMAT to open a
    connection to the MATLAB Engine, which in turns displays a MATLAB command
    window in the background. This connection is then used for all
    communication between GMAT and MATLAB until the connection is closed. Only
    one connection can be open at a time.</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Close</guilabel> menu item causes GMAT to close any
    open connection to the MATLAB Engine. If no connection is open, it has no
    effect.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Remarks</title>

    <refsection>
      <title xml:id="System_MatlabInterface_InterfaceSetup">Interface
      Setup</title>

      <para>The following conditions must be true for GMAT to successfully
      initiate communication with MATLAB. All conditions must be true for the
      same instance of MATLAB.</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="normal">
        <listitem>
          <para>A compatible, licensed version of MATLAB must be installed on
          the same machine on which GMAT is running. GMAT is tested with the
          latest version of MATLAB at the time of release, though versions
          R2006b and newer have been known to work.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The architecture (32-bit or 64-bit) of GMAT and the installed
          version of MATLAB must match. For example, the 32-bit version of
          GMAT is compatible only with the 32-bit version of MATLAB.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On Windows: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The following path (where
                <filename><replaceable>MATLAB</replaceable></filename> is the
                path to the installed version of MATLAB) must be present in
                the <envar>Path</envar> environment variable. For some older
                versions of MATLAB, this path must be present before the
                default Windows paths.</para>

                <para><filename><replaceable>MATLAB</replaceable>\bin\win32</filename>
                (or <filename>win64</filename> for use with 64-bit versions of
                GMAT)</para>

                <para/>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>MATLAB must be registered as a COM server. This is done
                automatically by the MATLAB installer. To do it manually, open
                an elevated command window and run the command:
                <userinput>matlab -regserver</userinput>. Make sure the proper
                instance of MATLAB is being run by this command.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On Mac OS X: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The MATLABFORGMAT environment variable must exist and
                contain the full path to the MATLAB application bundle (e.g.
                /Applications/MATLAB_R2010a/MATLAB_R2010a.app).</para>

                <para>Note that 64-bit GMAT must be used to interface with
                MATLAB after version R2010a.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>Common troubleshooting tips on Windows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you are using the officially-released 32-bit version of
            GMAT, make sure you have the 32-bit version of MATLAB
            installed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the path above exists in your system <envar>Path</envar>
            variable, try place it at the front.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure the same instance of MATLAB is referenced both in
            the <envar>Path</envar> variable and when running
            <userinput>matlab -regserver</userinput>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </note>
    </refsection>

    <refsection>
      <title>MATLAB Engine Connection</title>

      <warning>
        <para>Caution: GMAT does not close the MATLAB Command Window it
        creates after a run has completed. This allows manual inspection of
        the MATLAB workspace, but it can lead to confusing behavior if MATLAB
        functions or paths are changed and rerun in the same window.</para>

        <para>We recommend closing the MATLAB Command Window by right-clicking
        Matlab in the Resources tree and clicking Close between each run if
        you are actively editing the script.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>When GMAT runs a mission that contains a MATLAB function call, it
      opens a connection to the MATLAB engine before it makes the function
      call. It then reuses this connection for the rest of the GMAT
      session.</para>

      <para>The MATLAB Engine can be controlled manually through the
      <guilabel>Open</guilabel> and <guilabel>Close</guilabel> options
      available by right-clicking the <guilabel>Matlab</guilabel> item in the
      Resources tree.</para>
    </refsection>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>See the <xref linkend="MatlabFunction"/> reference for common
    examples.</para>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
