<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="MissionTree"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Mission Tree</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Mission Tree</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>The Mission Tree is an ordered, hierarchical, display of your GMAT
  script command mission sequence (everything after the
  <guilabel>BeginMissionSequence</guilabel> in your script). It represents the
  ordered list of commands to be executed to model your mission. The
  hierarchical grouping in the mission tree represent commands that are
  executed inside a control logic command, e.g., <guilabel>If</guilabel>,
  <guilabel>For</guilabel>, <guilabel>While</guilabel>, etc. The mission tree
  allows you to add, edit, delete and rename commands. It allows you to
  configure or filter the display of the commands in the Mission Tree to make
  the command execution easier to understand or modify. An example Mission
  Tree screenshot is below. The Mission Tree window is made up of 2 elements:
  the Mission Sequence on the left and the view filters toolbar on the
  right.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                   fileref="files/images/Using_MissionTree_GUI_1.png"
                   scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <warning>
    <para>Edits to the Mission Tree will be reflected in your script after it
    is synchronized and vice-versa. If you edit the Mission Tree, you need to
    synchronize with the script to see it in the script editor. If you edit
    the script, you need to synchronize with the GUI to see your changes
    reflected in the Mission Tree.</para>
  </warning>

  <section>
    <title>Mission Tree Display</title>

    <para>The Mission Tree Display shows your hierarchical, ordered list of
    commands. Normally, the Mission Tree displays only the command name in the
    tree for each command node (more information such as command type,
    construction information, etc can be displayed using the <guilabel>Show
    Detail</guilabel> menu option). Commands are executed in the order they
    appear, e.g., GMAT executes commands from the top of the Mission Tree to
    the bottom. For control logic (<guilabel>If</guilabel>,
    <guilabel>For</guilabel>, and <guilabel>While</guilabel>) and the
    <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel> and <guilabel>Target</guilabel> commands,
    you can define a block of commands that execute as children of the parent
    command. These child commands of the control logic or the
    <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel> and <guilabel>Target</guilabel> commands
    appear indented. Use the plus (<guilabel>+</guilabel>) symbol to the left
    of the control logic command to show all the grouped commands and the
    minus (<guilabel>-</guilabel>) symbol to hide all the grouped commands.
    Commands that are grouped under control logic commands (e.g.
    <guilabel>If</guilabel>, <guilabel>For</guilabel>, and
    <guilabel>While</guilabel>) only execute if that control logic command is
    successfully executed (e.g., if the local expression evaluates to true for
    <guilabel>If</guilabel> command, or the loop condition evaluates to true
    for <guilabel>For</guilabel> and <guilabel>While</guilabel>
    commands).</para>

    <para>In general, commands are executed only once. However, child commands
    grouped under the loop commands (e.g. <guilabel>For</guilabel> and
    <guilabel>While</guilabel>) may execute multiple times. These commands
    will execute for each time the loop command evaluates to true. Commands
    under the <guilabel>If</guilabel> commands are only executed if the
    <guilabel>If</guilabel> condition evaluates to true; otherwise, they are
    skipped. For the <guilabel>If-Else</guilabel> command, child commands
    grouped under the <guilabel>If</guilabel> portion of the command execute
    if the conditional statement evaluates to true; otherwise, the child
    commands grouped under the <guilabel>Else</guilabel> portion of the
    command execute.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Note that all commands in the Mission Tree are grouped under a
      special <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home item. This home item
      is always present as the first item in the Mission Tree and cannot be
      deleted.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>View Filters Toolbar</title>

    <para>The Mission Tree may display a subset of the commands of the full
    mission sequence based on your view filter options. There are 3 basic
    filtering options available within GMAT:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Filter by branch level</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Filter by command types (inclusive)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Filter by command types (exclusive)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The view filters activate by clicking one of the view filter buttons
    to the right of the Mission Tree. The pressed (pushed in) button indicates
    which filter is currently enabled. The four buttons on the top are the
    Filter by branch level buttons. The next four buttons in the middle are
    the inclusive filter-by-command-types buttons, and the four buttons on the
    bottom are the exclusive filter-by-command-types buttons. The button at
    the very bottom of the view filters toolbar allows you to define a custom
    filter. You cannot combine filter-by-branch-level filters with the
    filter-by-command-type filters nor combine inclusive and exclusive command
    type filters. However, multiple inclusive command type filters can be
    combined (e.g., filter both physics related and solver related commands)
    or multiple exclusive command type filters can be combined.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Note that all parents of a viewable command are displayed, even if
      the parent command is not part of the viewable command set.</para>

      <para>Also note that the Mission Tree automatically reconfigures to show
      all commands when the user Appends or Inserts a new command.</para>
    </note>

    <section>
      <title>Filter by Branch Level</title>

      <para>Filtering by branch level causes GMAT to not display commands in
      the mission tree that are below a certain level. To select the number of
      levels you wish to display, click the buttons on the top. The four
      buttons correspond to (from top to bottom):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show all branches</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Show one level of branching</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Show two levels of branching</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Show three levels of branching</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Only one filter-by-branch-level button may be active at a time.
      The default GMAT behavior is to display all branches of a mission
      tree.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Filter by Command Types</title>

      <para>GMAT allows you to filter what commands are displayed by their
      command type. You may select to only display commands that are in a
      filter command type set (inclusive) or only display commands that are
      not in a filter command type set (exclusive). GMAT provides both
      pre-configured command type sets (e.g., physics related or output
      related) and custom command type sets that you define</para>

      <para>The four middle buttons in the View Options toolbar are
      pre-configured inclusive command filters, e.g., only display commands
      that are in the desired command set. The four inclusive filter buttons
      correspond to (from top to bottom):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Physics Related (<guilabel>Propagate</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Maneuver</guilabel>, <guilabel>BeginFiniteBurn</guilabel>,
          and <guilabel>EndFiniteBurn</guilabel>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Solver Related (<guilabel>Target</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel>, <guilabel>Vary</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Achieve</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>NonlinearConstraint</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Minimize</guilabel>, <guilabel>EndTarget</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>EndOptimize</guilabel>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel> commands</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Control Flow (<guilabel>If</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>If-Else</guilabel>, <guilabel>For</guilabel>, and
          <guilabel>While</guilabel>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Multiple inclusive command type filters can be active at once. For
      example, to filter both physics related and solver related commands,
      click both the physics-related and solver-related filter buttons so that
      they appear pressed down. This option will show all physics related and
      solver related commands and hide all other commands (except Parents of
      the viewable commands)).</para>

      <para>The four buttons at the bottom in the View Options toolbar are
      pre-configured exclusive command filters, e.g., only display commands
      that are not in the command set. The four exclusive filter buttons
      correspond to (from top to bottom):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Report</guilabel></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Equation</guilabel></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Output-related (<guilabel>Report</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Toggle</guilabel>, <guilabel>PenUp</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>PenDown</guilabel>, <guilabel>MarkPoint</guilabel>, and
          <guilabel>ClearPlot</guilabel>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Function calls
          (<guilabel>CallMatlabFunction</guilabel>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Multiple exclusive command type filters can be active at once. For
      example, to show everything but <guilabel>Report</guilabel> and
      output-related commands, click both the <guilabel>Report</guilabel> and
      output-related filter buttons so that they appear pressed down.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Note that the Mission Tree shows an ellipsis (…) after a command
        name if the command is followed by items not graphically displayed in
        the tree because of filter options.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mission Sequence Menu</title>

    <para>The Mission Tree has two context-sensitive popup menus, depending on
    whether you right-click the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home
    item or a command in the Mission Tree. The <guilabel>Mission
    Sequence</guilabel> popup menu primarily allows you to manipulate the
    Mission Tree window and the entire command sequence. It also enables
    appending (adding to the end) commands to the mission tree.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/Using_MissionTree_MissionSequenceMenu.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para><guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> menu options are always
    available and active in the menu list.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Mission Sequence Menu Options:</title>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Collapse All</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>This menu option collapses all the branches in the Mission Tree
        so that you only see the top-level commands. To show branches, click
        the plus (<guilabel>+</guilabel>) button next to a command or select
        <guimenuitem>Expand All</guimenuitem> from the <guilabel>Mission
        Sequence</guilabel> popup menu.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Expand All</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>This menu option expands all the branches and sub-branches in
        the Mission Tree so that you see every command in the mission
        sequence. To hide branches, click the minus (<guilabel>-</guilabel>)
        button next to a command or select <guimenuitem>Collapse
        All</guimenuitem> from the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> popup
        menu.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem> menu option displays the
        submenu of commands that can be appended to the mission sequence. This
        menu is not available when the Mission Tree view is filtered.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem> menu option executes the
        mission command sequence. This menu option is always available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Show Detail</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Show Detail</guimenuitem> menu option toggles
        an option to display the mission tree with short or verbose text. When
        the show detail menu option is checked, each command is displayed with
        the script line for the command (e.g. what appears in “<guilabel>Show
        Script</guilabel>” for the command). When the show detail menu option
        is unchecked, the mission tree shows only the label for the command
        which will be your custom label if you have provided one and a system
        provided label if you have not labelled the command. This menu option
        is always available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Show Mission Sequence</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Show Mission Sequence</guimenuitem> menu option
        displays a streamlined text view of the mission sequence in text
        window. This view shows a hierarchical view of every command (similar
        to a script view) in the mission sequence. Unlike the script editor,
        this view only includes the command names and labels. This menu option
        is always available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Show Script</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Show Script</guimenuitem> menu option displays
        the script associated with the GUI version of the current mission
        script. This is the complete script that would be saved to a file if
        you clicked the GUI save button. Note that when the GUI is
        unsynchronized with the script editor (please see <xref
        linkend="ScriptEditor" xrefstyle="select:title"/> for more details),
        this mission script is different than the script displayed in the
        script editor. This menu option is always available</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Mission Summary - All</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Mission Summary - All</guimenuitem> menu option
        displays a mission simulation summary for the all commands in the
        mission sequence. This summary information includes spacecraft state
        information, spacecraft physical properties, time information,
        planetodetic properties, and other orbit data for each command. This
        information is only available after a mission simulation is run and
        the data shows state information after the execution of the command.
        Showing Mission Summary data for a <guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel>
        command is equivalent to showing summary data for the last command in
        that <guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel>. If commands are nested in
        control flow or solver branches, the summary data that is displayed is
        for the last pass through the sequence. This menu option is always
        available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Mission Summary - Physics</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Mission Summary - Physics</guimenuitem> menu
        option displays a mission simulation summary for physics related
        commands in the mission sequence. This summary information includes
        spacecraft state information, spacecraft physical properties, time
        information, planetodetic properties, and other orbit data for each
        command. This information is only available after a mission simulation
        is run and the data shows state information after the execution of the
        command. Note that if you have physics-based commands such as
        <guilabel>Propagate</guilabel> or <guilabel>Maneuver</guilabel> inside
        a <guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel> command, then summary information
        for those commands, are not displayed. Showing Mission Summary data
        for a <guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel> is equivalent to showing
        summary data for the last command in that
        <guilabel>ScriptEvent</guilabel>. If commands are nested in control
        flow or solver branches, the summary data that is displayed is for the
        last pass through the sequence. This menu option is always
        available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Dock Mission Tree</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Dock Mission Tree</guimenuitem> menu option
        docks the Mission Tree window in the notebook containing the Resources
        tree and Output tree. This option is only selectable if the Mission
        Tree is currently floating or undocked. Please see the
        Docking/Undocking/Placement section for more information.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Undock Mission Tree</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Undock Mission Tree</guimenuitem> menu option
        undocks, or makes floating, the Mission Tree window from the Resources
        tree and Output tree. The undocked Mission Tree window may be resized,
        moved, maximized, minimized, and restored. This option is only
        selectable if the Mission Tree is currently docked. Please see the
        <xref linkend="MissionTree_Docking"/> section for more
        information.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Command Menu</title>

    <para>The Command popup menu allows you to add, edit, or delete the
    commands in the Mission Tree by using the right mouse button. This
    displays a context sensitive menu for adding and modifying commands as
    well as viewing your command sequence and command summary. To add commands
    to the Mission Tree, right click a command and select
    <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Insert
    Before</guimenuitem>, or <guimenuitem>Insert After</guimenuitem>. To edit
    commands, double click the command name or right click and select
    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>.</para>

    <para>Most commands in GMAT can appear anywhere in the mission sequence.
    However, there are some exceptions and the Command popup menu is context
    sensitive, meaning the options available under the menu change based on
    what command is selected and where in the tree the command occurs. Here is
    a complete list of context sensitivities:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guimenuitem>Insert</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem> are not available unless the mission
        tree filter is set to show all levels.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Achieve</guilabel> commands can only appear inside of
        a <guilabel>Target</guilabel> sequence.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Vary</guilabel> commands can only appear in a
        <guilabel>Target</guilabel> or <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel>
        sequence,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>NonlinearConstraint</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Minimize</guilabel> commands can only appear in an
        <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel> sequence.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="files/images/Using_MissionTree_GUI_4.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Command Menu Options</title>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>This menu option opens the command editor window for the
        selected command. The <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu option is
        always active in the menu list. If the window is already open, the
        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> option brings the window to the front
        and makes it the active window.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>This menu options closes the command editor window for the
        selected command. The <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> menu option is
        always active in the menu list.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem> menu option displays the
        submenu of commands that can be appended as the last sub-item of the
        selected command in the Mission Tree. As such, the
        <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem> menu option only appears when the
        selected tree item can contain sub-items, e.g., the <guilabel>Mission
        Sequence</guilabel> home item, control logic commands, and
        <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel> and <guilabel>Target</guilabel>
        commands. Note that the <guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem> submenu is
        context-sensitive and will only show commands that may be appended to
        the selected command. Finally, this menu is not available when the
        Mission Tree view is filtered.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Insert After</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Insert After</guimenuitem> menu option displays
        the submenu of commands that can be inserted after the selected
        command (and any child commands, if any) in the Mission Tree.
        Nominally, the new command is inserted at the same level as the
        selected command. However, if the selected command is the “End”
        command of a control logic or <guilabel>Optimize</guilabel> or
        <guilabel>Target</guilabel> command (e.g., <guilabel>End
        For</guilabel>, <guilabel>End If</guilabel>, <guilabel>End
        Optimize</guilabel>, etc), the new command is inserted after the
        <guilabel>End</guilabel> command and on the same level (e.g., the next
        level up) as the parent command. The <guimenuitem>Insert
        After</guimenuitem> menu option is always active in the menu list
        except when the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home item is
        selected. Note that the <guimenuitem>Insert After</guimenuitem>
        submenu is context-sensitive and will only show commands that may be
        added after the selected command. Finally, this menu is not available
        when the Mission Tree view is filtered.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Insert Before</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Insert Before</guimenuitem> menu option
        displays the submenu of commands that can be inserted before the
        selected command (and any child commands, if any) in the Mission Tree.
        The new command is always inserted at the same level as the selected
        command. The Insert Before menu option is always active in the menu
        list except when the Mission Sequence Home item is selected. Note that
        the <guimenuitem>Insert Before</guimenuitem> submenu is
        context-sensitive and will only show commands that may be added before
        the selected command. Finally, this menu is not available when the
        Mission Tree view is filtered.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem> menu option displays a
        dialog box where you can rename the selected command. A command name
        may contain any characters except the single quote. Note that, unlike
        resources, command names do not have to be unique. The
        <guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem> menu option is always active in the
        menu list except when the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home
        item is selected.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> menu option deletes the
        selected command. GMAT does not confirm the option before deletion
        occurs. The <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> menu option is always
        active in the menu list except when the <guilabel>Mission
        Sequence</guilabel> home item is selected.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><guimenuitem>Command Summary</guimenuitem></title>

        <para>The <guimenuitem>Command Summary</guimenuitem> menu option
        displays a mission simulation summary for the selected command,
        including spacecraft state information, time information, planetodetic
        properties, and other orbit data. This information is only available
        after a mission simulation run. This menu option is always available.
        However, command summary data is not available for
        <guilabel>Propagate</guilabel> command in single step mode. The button
        is available but no data is displayed.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="MissionTree_Docking">
    <title>Docking/Undocking/Placement</title>

    <para>The Mission Tree window may be used as a floating window or docked
    with the Resource tree. GMAT remembers the placement and docking status of
    the Mission Tree even after you quit. The undocked Mission Tree window may
    be resized, moved, or minimized. When the Mission Tree is undocked, and
    the user opens a dialog box for a GUI component, the dialog box does not
    cover the Mission Tree.</para>

    <para>To undock the Mission Tree Display, either:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Right click and drag the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tab out of
        the Resource Tree window.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Right click the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home item
        and select <guimenuitem>Undock Mission Tree</guimenuitem>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To dock the Mission Tree display, either:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Left click the close button (<guibutton>x</guibutton>) of the
        undocked Mission Tree window.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>RIght click the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel> home item
        and select <guimenuitem>Dock Mission Tree</guimenuitem>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
