<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="CommandSummary"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Command Summary</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Command Summary</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>The <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> is a summary of orbit and
  spacecraft state information after execution of a command. For example, if
  the command is a <guilabel>Propagate</guilabel> command, the
  <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> contains state data after propagation
  is performed.</para>

  <para>To view the <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel>, right-click on the
  desired command, and select <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel>. Or
  alternatively, double-click on the desired command, and click the
  <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> icon located near the lower left corner
  of the panel. You must run the mission before viewing <guilabel>Command
  Summary</guilabel> data.</para>

    <para>Snapshot of a sample <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> is shown in the following figure.</para>
	
  <screenshot>
    <info>
      <title/>
    </info>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                   fileref="files/images/Using_CommandSummary_DefaultMission.png"
                   scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <section>
    <title>Data Availability</title>

    <para>To view a <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel>, you must first run
    the mission. If the mission has not been run during the current session,
    the <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> will be empty. If changes are
    made to your configuration, you must rerun the mission for those changes
    to take effect in the <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Data Contents</title>

    <para>The <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> contains several types of
    data. Orbit state representations include Cartesian, spherical, and
    Keplerian. For hyperbolic orbits, B-Plane coordinates, DLA and RLA are
    provided. Planetodetic information includes Longitude and Latitude among
    others. For a <guilabel>Maneuver</guilabel> command, the <guilabel>Maneuver</guilabel>
    properties are displayed in the CoordinateSystem specified on the
    <guilabel>ImpulsiveBurn</guilabel> resource. See the Coordinate Systems subsection below
    for more information on the command summary contents when some data is undefined.</para>

    <para>In the event when the orbit is nearly singular conic section and/or any of the
    keplerian elements are undefined, an abbreviated <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> is displayed
    as shown in the Coordinate Systems subsection below.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Supported Commands</title>

    <para>For performance reasons, propagation in step mode does not write out
    a command summary. Additionally, if a command is nested in control logic
    and that command does not execute as a result, no command summary data is
    available.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Coordinate Systems</title>

    <para>The <guilabel>Coordinate System</guilabel> menu at the top of the
    <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> dialog allows you to select the
    desired coordinate system for the state data. When the <guilabel>Coordinate System</guilabel>
    has a celestial body at the origin, the <guilabel>Command Summary</guilabel> shows all supported
    data including Cartesian, Spherical, Keplerian, Other OrbitData, and Planetodetic properties as shown
    in the GUI screenshot above. When the <guilabel>Coordinate System</guilabel> does not have a
    celestial body at the origin, the <guilabel>CommandSummary</guilabel> contains an abbreviated command summary
    as shown below.</para> 

    <para>Note: GMAT currently requires that the selected <guilabel>CoordinateSystem</guilabel> cannot
    reference a spacecraft.</para>

    <programlisting><code>Propagate Command: Propagate1
        Spacecraft       : DefaultSC
        Coordinate System: EarthMJ2000Eq

        Time System   Gregorian                     Modified Julian  
        --------------------------------------------------------------------    
        UTC Epoch:    01 Jan 2000 15:19:28.000      21545.1385185185
        TAI Epoch:    01 Jan 2000 15:20:00.000      21545.1388888889
        TT  Epoch:    01 Jan 2000 15:20:32.184      21545.1392613889
        TDB Epoch:    01 Jan 2000 15:20:32.184      21545.1392613881

        Cartesian State                       Spherical State 
        ---------------------------           ------------------------------ 
        X  =   7047.3574396928 km             RMAG =   7195.1179781105 km
        Y  =  -821.00373455465 km             RA   =  -6.6448962577676 deg 
        Z  =   1196.0053110175 km             DEC  =   9.5683789596091 deg 
        VX =   0.8470865225276 km/sec         VMAG =   7.4415324037805 km/s
        VY =   7.3062391027010 km/sec         AZI  =   81.377585410118 deg
        VZ =   1.1303623817297 km/sec         VFPA =   88.583915406742 deg  
                                              RAV  =   83.386645244484 deg
                                              DECV =   8.7370006427902 deg

        Spacecraft Properties 
        ------------------------------
        Cd                    =   2.200000
        Drag area             =   15.00000 m^2
        Cr                    =   1.800000
        Reflective (SRP) area =   1.000000 m^2
        Dry mass              =   850.00000000000 kg
        Total mass            =   850.00000000000 kg</code></programlisting>
  </section>
</section>
