<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="WelcomeToGmat"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="Welcome">Welcome to GMAT</title>

  <para>Do you want to go Mars but don't know when to leave or how much to
  bring? Do you want to study Earth protection by planning a mission to a
  near-Earth asteroid? The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) is an
  open-source space mission design tool to answer just those types of
  questions. GMAT is designed to model and optimize spacecraft trajectories in
  flight regimes ranging from low Earth orbit to lunar, libration point , and
  deep space missions. GMAT is developed by a team of NASA, private industry,
  public, and private contributors and is used for real-world engineering
  studies, as a tool for education and public engagement, and starting in
  Sept. 2013 to fly operational spacecraft.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Features Overview</title>

    <para>GMAT is a feature rich system containing high fidelity space system
    models, optimization and targeting, built in scripting and programming
    infrastructure, and customizable plots, reports and data products, to
    enable flexible analysis and solutions for custom and unique applications.
    GMAT can be driven from a fully featured, interactive GUI or from a custom
    script language. Here are some of GMAT’s key features broken down by
    feature group.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Dynamics and Environment Modelling</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>High fidelity dynamics models including harmonic gravity,
          drag, tides, and relativistic corrections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>High fidelity spacecraft modeling</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Formations and constellations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Impulsive and finite maneuver modeling and optimization</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propulsion system modeling including tanks and
          thrusters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Solar System modeling including high fidelity ephemerides,
          custom celestial bodies, libration points, and barycenters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rich set of coordinate system including J2000, ICRF, fixed,
          rotating, topocentric, and many others</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SPICE kernel propagation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propagators that naturally synchronize epochs of multiple
          vehicles and avoid fixed step integration and interpolation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Plotting, Reporting and Product Generation</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interactive 3-D graphics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Customizable data plots and reports</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Post computation animation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CCSDS, SPK, and Code-500 ephemeris generation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optimization and Targeting</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Boundary value targeters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Nonlinear, constrained optimization</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom, scriptable cost functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom, scriptable nonlinear equality and inequality
          constraint functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom targeter controls and constraints</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Programming Infrastructure</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>User defined variables, arrays, and strings</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User defined equations using MATLAB syntax. (i.e. overloaded
          array operation)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Control flow such as If, For, and While loops for custom
          applications</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matlab interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Built in parameters and calculations in multiple coordinate
          systems</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Interfaces</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fully featured, interactive GUI that makes simple analysis
          quick and easy</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom scripting language that makes complex, custom analysis
          possible</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matlab interface for custom external simulations and
          calculations</para>
        </listitem>

		<listitem>
          <para>File interface for the TCOPS Vector Hold File format, for
		  loading of initial spacecraft data</para>
        </listitem>
		
        <listitem>
          <para>Command line interface for batch analysis</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Licensing</title>

    <para>GMAT is licensed under the Apache License 2.0.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Platform Support</title>

    <para>GMAT has been rigorously tested on the Windows 7 platform and we
    perform nightly regression tests running almost 11,000 test cases for the
    script engine and over 4000 test cases for the GUI interface.</para>

    <para>While the system is routinely built on Mac and Linux, we consider
    the software to be in alpha form on those plaforms. For release R2013b, we
    have only addressed issues on Mac and Linux that also occur on the Windows
    7 platform. Part of our planning effort for the next release will be to
    assess the future of GMAT on Mac and Linux.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Development Status and Usage</title>

    <para>R2013a is a major maintenance release with completely updated
    documentation and greatly improved quality. GMAT is no longer Beta
    software. Historically, solutions from GMAT have been verified in other
    operational systems. However, with release R2013a, the GMAT team will
    perform final operational certifications testing of the system be
    completed in the summer of 2013. After completion of operational
    certification, GMAT will be used for operational support of flight
    projects.</para>

    <para>GMAT has been used to optimize maneuvers for flight projects such as
    NASA’s LCROSS and ARTEMIS missions, and the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
    (LRO). ARTEMIS and LRO flew trajectories optimized in GMAT and verified in
    the operational ground system. GMAT has been used extensively for launch
    window verification for OSIRIS-REx. The MMS project has used GMAT for
    formation maneuver planning and Monte Carlo analysis. GMAT has been used
    on numerous concept studies from Earth-Sun libration point missions, LEO
    missions, lunar missions, and interplanetary missions to Venus, Mars,
    Jupiter, and near-Earth and Trojan asteroids.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <para>The Navigation and Mission Design Branch at NASA’s Goddard Space
    Flight Center performs project management activities and is involved in
    most phases of the development process including requirements, algorithms,
    design, and testing. The Ground Software Systems Branch performs design,
    implementation, and integration testing. Commecial particpants contribute
    to design, implementation, testing and documentation. Commercial
    participants for R2013b include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thinking Systems, Inc. (system architecture and all aspects of
        development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a.i. solutions (testing)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Past commercial and external contributors to GMAT include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Air Force Research Lab (all aspects of development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Boeing (algorithms and testing)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Schafer Corporation (all aspects of development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Honeywell Technology Solutions (testing)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Computer Sciences Corporation (requirements)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) has provided funding for
    integration of the SPICE toolkit into GMAT. Additionally, the European
    Space Agency’s (ESA) Advanced Concepts team has developed optimizer
    plug-ins for the Non-Linear Programming (NLP) solvers SNOPT (Sparse
    Nonlinear OPTimizer) and IPOPT (Interior Point OPTimizer).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
