<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="ConfiguringGmat"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Configuring GMAT</title>

  <para>Below we discuss the files and data that are distributed with GMAT and
  are required for GMAT execution. GMAT uses many types of data files,
  including planetary ephemeris files, Earth orientation data, leap second
  files, and gravity coefficient files. This section describes how these files
  are organized and the controls provided to customize them.</para>

  <section>
    <title xml:id="ConfiguringGmat_FileStructure">File Structure</title>

    <para>The default directory structure for GMAT is broken into eight main
    subdirectories, as shown in <xref linkend="GmatRootDirectoryStructure"/>.
    These directories organize the files and data used to run GMAT, including
    binary libraries, data files, texture maps, and 3D models. The only two
    files in the GMAT root directory are <filename>license.txt</filename>,
    which contains the text of the Apache License 2.0, and
    <filename>README.txt</filename>, which contains user information for the
    current GMAT release. A summary of the contents of each subdirectory is
    provided in the sections below.</para>

    <figure xml:id="GmatRootDirectoryStructure">
      <title>GMAT Root Directory Structure</title>

      <screenshot>
        <info>
          <title/>
        </info>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="files/images/Util_DirectoryStructure.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title><filename>bin</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>bin</filename> directory contains all binary files
      required for the core functionality of GMAT. These libraries include the
      executable file (<filename>GMAT.exe</filename> on Windows,
      <filename>GMAT.app</filename> on the Mac, and <filename>GMAT</filename>
      on Linux) and platform-specific support libraries. The
      <filename>bin</filename> directory also contains two text files:
      <filename>gmat_startup_file.txt</filename> and
      <filename>gmat.ini</filename>. The startup file is discussed in detail
      in a separate section below. The <filename>gmat.ini</filename> file is
      used to configure some GUI panels, set paths to external web links, and
      define GUI tooltip messages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>data</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>data</filename> directory contains all required data
      files to run GMAT and is organized according to data type, as shown in
      <xref linkend="GmatDataDirectoryStructure"/> and described below.</para>

      <figure xml:id="GmatDataDirectoryStructure">
        <title>GMAT Data Directory Structure</title>

        <screenshot>
          <info>
            <title/>
          </info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="files/images/Util_DirectoryStructure_Data.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>The <filename>graphics</filename> directory contains data files
      for GMAT’s visualization utilities, as well as application icons and
      images. The <filename>splash</filename> directory contains the GMAT
      splash screen that is displayed briefly while GMAT is initializing. The
      <filename>stars</filename> directory contains a star catalogue used for
      displaying stars in 3D graphics. The texture folder contains texture
      maps used for the 2D and 3D graphics resources. The
      <filename>icons</filename> directory contains graphics files for icons
      and images loaded at run time, such as the GMAT logo and GUI
      icons.</para>

      <para>The <filename>gravity</filename> directory contains gravity
      coefficient files for each body with a default non-spherical gravity
      model. Within each directory, the coefficient files are named according
      to the model they represent, and use the extension
      <filename>.cof</filename>.</para>

      <para>The <filename>gui_config</filename> directory contains files for
      configuring some of the GUI dialog boxes for GMAT resources and
      commands. These files allow you to easily create a GUI panel for a
      user-provided plugin, and are also used by some of the built-in GUI
      panels.</para>

      <para>The <filename>planetary_coeff</filename> directory contains the
      Earth orientation parameters (EOP) provided by the International Earth
      Rotation Service (IERS) and nutation coefficients for different nutation
      theories.</para>

      <para>The <filename>planetary_ephem</filename> directory contains
      planetary ephemeris data in both DE and SPK formats. The
      <filename>de</filename> directory contains the binary digital ephemeris
      DE405 files for the 8 planets, the Moon, and Pluto developed and
      distributed by JPL. The <filename>spk</filename> directory contains the
      DE421 SPICE kernel and kernels for selected comets, asteroids and moons.
      All ephemeris files distributed with GMAT are in the little-endian
      format.</para>

      <para>The <filename>time</filename> directory contains the JPL leap
      second kernel <filename>naif0010.tls</filename> and the GMAT leap second
      file <filename>tai-utc.dat</filename>.</para>

      <para>The <filename>vehicle</filename> directory contains ephemeris data
      and 3D models for selected spacecraft. The <filename>ephem</filename>
      directory contains SPK ephemeris files, including orbit, attitude,
      frame, and time kernels. The <filename>models</filename> directory
      contains 3D model files in 3DS or POV format for use by GMAT’s
      <classname>OrbitView</classname> visualization resource.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>docs</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>docs</filename> directory contains end-user
      documentation, including draft PDF versions of the Mathematical
      Specification, Architectural Specification, and Estimation
      Specification. The GMAT User’s Guide is available in the
      <filename>help</filename> directory in PDF and HTML formats, and as a
      Windows HTML Help file.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>extras</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>extras</filename> directory contains various extra
      convenience files that are helpful for working with GMAT but aren't part
      of the core codebase. The only file here so far is a syntax coloring
      file for the GMAT scripting language in the Notepad++ text
      editor.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>matlab</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>matlab</filename> directory contains M-files
      required for GMAT’s MATLAB interfaces, including the interface to the
      fmincon optimizer. All files in the <filename>matlab</filename>
      directory and its subdirectories must be included in your MATLAB path
      for the MATLAB interfaces to function properly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>output</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>output</filename> directory is the default location
      for file output such as ephemeris files and report files. If no path
      information is provided for reports or ephemeris files created during a
      GMAT session, then those files will be written to the output
      folder.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>plugins</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>plugins</filename> directory contains optional
      plugins that are not required for use of GMAT. The
      <filename>proprietary</filename> directory is used for for third-party
      libraries that cannot be distributed freely and is an empty folder in
      the open source distribution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>samples</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>samples</filename> directory contains over 45 sample
      missions, ranging from a Hohmann transfer to libration point
      station-keeping to Mars B-plane targeting. Example files begin with
      "Ex_" and files that corresponde to GMAT tutorials begin with "Tut_".
      These files are intended to demonstrate GMAT’s capabilities and to
      provide you with a potential starting point for building common mission
      types for your application and flight regime. Samples with specific
      requirements are located in subdirectories such as
      <filename>NeedMatlab</filename> and
      <filename>NeedVF13ad</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><filename>userfunctions</filename></title>

      <para>The <filename>userfunctions</filename> directory contains MATLAB
      functions that are included in the GMAT distribution. You can also store
      your own custom MATLAB functions in this folders.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title xml:id="ConfiguringGmat_DataFiles">Configuring Data Files</title>

    <para>You can configure the data files GMAT loads at run time by editing
    the <filename>gmat_startup_file.txt</filename> file located in the
    <filename>bin</filename> directory. The startup file contains path
    information for data files such as ephemeris, Earth orientation parameters
    and graphics files. By editing the startup file, you can customize which
    files are loaded and used during a GMAT session. Below we describe the
    customization features available in the startup file. The order of lines
    in the startup file does not matter.</para>

    <para>For all details, see the <xref linkend="StartupFile"/>
    reference.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Leap Second and EOP files</title>

      <para>GMAT reads several files that are used for high fidelity modelling
      of time and coordinate systems: the leap second files and the Earth
      orientation parameters (EOP) provided by the IERS. The EOP file is
      updated daily by the IERS. To update your local file with the latest
      data, simply replace the file <filename>eopc04_08.62-now</filename> in
      the <filename>data/planetary_coeff</filename> directory. Updated
      versions of this file are available from the <link
      xlink:href="http://data.iers.org/products/213/14444/orig/eopc04_08.62-now">IERS</link>.</para>

      <para>There are two leap second files provided with GMAT in the
      <filename>data/time</filename> directory. The
      <filename>naif0010.tls</filename> file is used by the JPL SPICE
      libraries when computing ephemerides. When a new leap second is added,
      you can replace this file with the new file from <link
      xlink:href="ftp://naif.jpl.nasa.gov/pub/naif/generic_kernels/lsk/">NAIF</link>.
      GMAT reads the<filename> tai-utc.dat</filename> file for all time
      computations requiring leap seconds that are not performed by the SPICE
      utilities. When a new leap second is added, you can replace this file
      with the new file from the <link
      xlink:href="ftp://maia.usno.navy.mil/ser7/tai-utc.dat">US Naval
      Observatory</link>. In addtion, you can modify the file if a new leap
      second is added by simply duplicating the last row and updating it with
      the correct information for the new leap second. For example, if a new
      leapsecond were added on 01 Jul 2013, you would add the following line
      to the bottom of <filename>tai-utc.dat</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>2013 JUL 1 =JD 2456474.5 TAI-UTC= 35.0 S + (MJD - 41317.) X 0.0</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Loading Custom Plugins</title>

      <para>Custom plugins are loaded by adding a line to the startup file
      (<filename>bin/gmat_startup_file.txt</filename>) specifying the name and
      location of the plugin file. In order for a plugin to work with GMAT,
      the plugin library must be placed in the folder referenced in the
      startup file. For all details, see the <xref linkend="StartupFile"/>
      reference.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the MATLAB Inteface</title>

      <para>GMAT contains an interface to MATLAB. See the <xref
      linkend="MatlabInterface"/> reference to configure the MATLAB
      interface.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User-defined Function Paths</title>

      <para>If you create custom MATLAB functions, you can provide the path to
      those files and GMAT will locate them at run time. The default startup
      file is configured so you can place MATLAB functions (with a
      <filename>.m</filename> extension) in the
      <filename>userfunctions/matlab</filename> directory. GMAT automatically
      searches that location at run time. You can change the location of the
      search path to your MATLAB functions by changing these lines in your
      startup file to reflect the location of your files with respect to the
      GMAT <filename>bin</filename> folder:</para>

      <programlisting>MATLAB_FUNCTION_PATH = ../userfunctions/matlab</programlisting>

      <para>If you wish to organize your custom functions in multiple folders,
      you can add multiple search paths to the startup file. For
      example,</para>

      <programlisting>MATLAB_FUNCTION_PATH = ../MyFunctions/utils
MATLAB_FUNCTION_PATH = ../MyFunctions/StateConversion 
MATLAB_FUNCTION_PATH = ../MyFunctions/TimeConversion</programlisting>

      <para>GMAT will search the paths in the order specified in the startup
      file and will use the first function with a matching name.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
