<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="WelcomeToGmat"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="Welcome">Welcome to GMAT</title>

  <para>The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) is the world’s only
  enterprise, multi-mission, open source software system for space mission
  design, optimization, and navigation. The system supports missions in flight
  regimes ranging from low Earth orbit to lunar, libration point, and deep
  space missions. GMAT is developed by a team of NASA, private industry,
  public, and private contributors and is used for real-world mission support,
  engineering studies, as a tool for education, and public engagement.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Features Overview</title>

    <para>GMAT is a feature rich system containing high fidelity space system
    models, optimization and targeting, built in scripting and programming
    infrastructure, and customizable plots, reports and data products, to
    enable flexible analysis and solutions for custom and unique applications.
    GMAT can be driven from a fully featured, interactive GUI or from a custom
    script language. Here are some of GMAT’s key features broken down by
    feature group.</para>

    <para>Release R2016a is the first version of GMAT to contain production
    navigation functionality. We've also added the ability to read and export
    script snippets from external files, the ability to write STK .e ephem
    files, and added many new built-in math functions. See the <link
    linkend="ReleaseNotesR2016a">R2016a Release Notes</link> for other
    additions and bug fixes.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Dynamics and Environment Modelling</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>High fidelity dynamics models including harmonic gravity,
          drag, tides, and relativistic corrections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>High fidelity spacecraft modeling</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Formations and constellations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Impulsive and finite maneuver modeling and optimization</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propulsion system modeling including chemical and electric
          system</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Solar System modeling including high fidelity ephemerides,
          custom celestial bodies, libration points, and barycenters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rich set of coordinate system including J2000, ICRF, fixed,
          rotating, topocentric, and many others</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SPICE kernel propagation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propagators that naturally synchronize epochs of multiple
          vehicles and avoid fixed step integration and interpolation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Plotting, Reporting and Product Generation</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interactive 3-D graphics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Customizable data plots and reports</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Post computation animation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CCSDS, SPK, and Code-500 ephemeris generation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Eclipse and station contact location</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optimization and Targeting</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Boundary value targeters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Nonlinear, constrained optimization</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom, scriptable cost functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom, scriptable nonlinear equality and inequality
          constraint functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom targeter controls and constraints</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Programming Infrastructure</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>User defined variables, arrays, and strings</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User defined equations using MATLAB syntax. (i.e. overloaded
          array operation)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Control flow such as If, For, and While loops for custom
          applications</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matlab interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Python interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User-defined functions (sub-routines)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Built in parameters and calculations in multiple coordinate
          systems</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Orbit Determination Infrastructure</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Batch estimator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Extensive statistical results reporting</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DSN data types</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Beta SN and GN data types (turned off but can be turned on for
          experimentation)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Measurement data editing</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Media corrections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Error modeling</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Interfaces</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fully featured, interactive GUI that makes simple analysis
          quick and easy</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom scripting language that makes complex, custom analysis
          possible</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matlab interface for custom external simulations and
          calculations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Python interface for custom external simulations and
          calculations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>File interface for the TCOPS Vector Hold File format, for
          loading of initial spacecraft data</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Command line interface for batch analysis</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Heritage</title>

    <para>GMAT has enabled and enhanced missions in nearly every NASA flight
    regime including enabling new mission types, extending the life of
    existing missions, and enabling new science observations. GMAT has
    supported 8 NASA missions and 10+ NASA proposal efforts. The system has
    experienced broad application and adoption around the world. To date, GMAT
    has been used by over 30 organizations, with 15 universities and 12
    commercial firms publishing results in the open literature.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Licensing</title>

    <para>GMAT is licensed under the Apache License 2.0.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Platform Support</title>

    <para>GMAT has been rigorously tested on the Windows 7 platform and we
    perform nightly regression tests running almost 13,000 test cases for the
    system core and over 4000 test cases for the GUI interface.</para>

    <para>For release R2016a, we have addressed issues on Windows including
    the GUI, and the Mac and Linux console (GUI is provided but is in alpha
    form on Mac and Linux).</para>

    <para>Note that this is the last 32-bit version of GMAT on Windows. Future
    versions will be 64-bit on all platforms.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <para>The Navigation and Mission Design Branch at NASA’s Goddard Space
    Flight Center performs project management activities and is involved in
    most phases of the development process including requirements, algorithms,
    design, and testing. The Ground Software Systems Branch performs design,
    implementation, and integration testing. External particpants contribute
    to design, implementation, testing and documentation. We use a
    collaborative development model that enables innovation and actively
    involves the public and private sector having seen contributions from 12
    commercial firms. External participants for R2015a include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thinking Systems, Inc. (system architecture and all aspects of
        development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Omitron, Inc (testing, requirements, specifications)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Emergent Space Technologies, Inc.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Korea Aerospace Research Institute</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Chonbuk National University, South Korea</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Yonsei University, South Korea</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Past commercial and external contributors to GMAT include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Air Force Research Lab (all aspects of development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Boeing (algorithms and testing)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Schafer Corporation (all aspects of development)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Honeywell Technology Solutions (testing)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Computer Sciences Corporation (requirements)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) has provided funding for
    integration of the SPICE toolkit into GMAT. Additionally, the European
    Space Agency’s (ESA) Advanced Concepts team has developed optimizer
    plug-ins for the Non-Linear Programming (NLP) solvers SNOPT (Sparse
    Nonlinear OPTimizer) and IPOPT (Interior Point OPTimizer).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
