<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="UserInterfaces"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>User Interfaces Overview</title>

  <para>GMAT offers multiple ways to design and execute your mission. The two
  primary interfaces are the graphical user interface (GUI) and the script
  interface. These interfaces are interchangeable and each supports most of
  the functionality available in GMAT. When you work in the script interface,
  you are working in GMAT’s custom script language. To avoid issues such as
  circular dependencies, there are some basic rules you must follow. Below, we
  discuss these interfaces and then discuss the basic rules and best practices
  for working in each interface.</para>

  <section>
    <title>GUI Overview</title>

    <para>When you start a session, the GMAT desktop is displayed with a
    default mission already loaded. The GMAT desktop has a native look and
    feel on each platform and most desktop components are supported on all
    platforms.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Windows GUI</title>

      <para>When you open GMAT on Windows and click <guiicon>Run</guiicon> in
      the Toolbar, GMAT executes the default mission as shown in the figure
      below. The tools listed below the figure are available in the GMAT
      desktop.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>GMAT Desktop (Windows)</title>

        <screenshot>
          <info>
            <title/>
          </info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="files/images/Intro_GettingStarted_WindowsGUI.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Menu Bar</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The menu bar contains <guimenu>File</guimenu>,
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, <guimenu>Window</guimenu> and
            <guimenu>Help</guimenu> functionality.</para>

            <para>On Windows, the <guilabel>File</guilabel> menu contains
            standard <guilabel>Open</guilabel>, <guilabel>Save</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Save As</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Exit</guilabel>
            functionality as well as <guilabel>Open Recent</guilabel>. The
            <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> menu contains functionality for script
            editing when the script editor is active. The
            <guilabel>Window</guilabel> menu contains tools for organizing
            graphics windows and the script editor within the GMAT desktop.
            Examples include the ability to <guilabel>Tile</guilabel> windows,
            <guilabel>Cascade</guilabel> windows and
            <guilabel>Close</guilabel> windows. The Help menu contains links
            to <guilabel>Online Help</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Tutorials</guilabel>, <guilabel>Forums</guilabel>, and
            the <guilabel>Report An Issue</guilabel> option links to GMAT’s
            defect reporting system, the <guilabel>Welcome Page</guilabel>,
            and a <guilabel>Provide Feedback</guilabel> link.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Toolbar</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The toolbar provides easy access to frequently used controls
            such as file controls, <guilabel>Run</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Pause</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Stop</guilabel> for
            mission execution, and controls for graphics animation. On Windows
            and Linux, the toolbar is located at the top of the GMAT window;
            on the Mac, it is located on the left of the GMAT frame. Because
            the toolbar is vertical on the Mac, some toolbar options are
            abbreviated.</para>

            <para>GMAT allows you to simultaneously edit the raw script file
            representation of your mission and the GUI representation of your
            mission. It is possible to make inconsistent changes in these
            mission representations. The <guilabel>GUI/Script Sync
            Status</guilabel> indicator located in the toolbar shows you the
            state of the two mission representations. See the <xref
            linkend="GuiScriptInteractionsAndSynchronization"/> section for
            further discussion.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Resources Tab</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tab brings the
            <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree to the foreground of the
            desktop.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Resources Tree</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree displays all
            configured GMAT resources and organizes them into logical groups.
            All objects created in a GMAT script using a <guilabel>Create
            </guilabel>command are found in the <guilabel>Resources</guilabel>
            tree in the GMAT desktop.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mission Tab</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tab brings the Mission Tree
            to the foreground of the desktop.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mission Tree</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tree displays GMAT commands
            that control the time-ordered sequence of events in a mission. The
            <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tree contains all script lines that
            occur after the <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command
            in a GMAT script. You can undock the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel>
            tree as shown in the figure below by right-clicking on the
            <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tab and dragging it into the graphics
            window. You can also follow these steps:</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click on the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tab to bring
                the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> Tree to the
                foreground.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Right-click on the <guilabel>Mission Sequence</guilabel>
                folder in the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tree and select
                <guilabel>Undock Mission Tree</guilabel> in the menu.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <figure>
              <title>Undocked Mission Tree</title>

              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                               fileref="files/images/Intro_GettingStarted_UndockedMissionTree.png"
                               scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Output Tab</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Output</guilabel> tab brings the Output Tree
            to the foreground of the desktop.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Output Tree</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Output</guilabel> tree contains GMAT output
            such as report files and graphical displays.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Message Window</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you run a mission in GMAT, information including
            warnings, errors, and progress are written to the message window.
            For example, if there is a syntax error in a script file, a
            detailed error message is written to the message window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Status Bar</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The status bar contains various informational messages about
            the state of the GUI. When a mission is running, a
            <guilabel>Busy</guilabel> indicator will appear in the left pane.
            The center pane displays the latitude and logitude of the mouse
            cursor as it moves over a ground track window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Script Interface Overview</title>

    <para>The GMAT script editor is a textual interface that lets you directly
    edit your mission in GMAT's built-in scripting language. In <xref
    linkend="Fig_ScriptEditor"/> below, the script editor is shown maximized
    in the GMAT desktop and the items relevant to script editing are
    labeled.</para>

    <figure xml:id="Fig_ScriptEditor">
      <title>GMAT Script Editor</title>

      <screenshot>
        <info>
          <title/>
        </info>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="files/images/Intro_GettingStarted_ScriptEditor.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Scripts Folder</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The GMAT desktop allows you to have multiple script files open
          simultaneously. Open script files are displayed in the
          <guilabel>Scripts</guilabel> folder in the
          <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree. Double click on a script in the
          <guilabel>Scripts</guilabel> folder to open it in the script editor.
          The GMAT desktop displays each script in a separate script editor.
          GMAT indicates the script currently represented in the GUI with a
          boldface name. Only one script can be loaded into the GUI at a
          time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Script Status Box</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>Script Status</guilabel> box indicates whether
          or not the script being edited is loaded in the GUI. The box says
          <guilabel>Active Script</guilabel> for the script currently
          represented in the GUI and <guilabel>Inactive Script</guilabel> for
          all others.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save,Sync Button</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>Save,Sync</guilabel> button saves any script
          file changes to disk, makes the script active, and synchronizes the
          GUI with the script.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save,Sync,Run Button</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>Save,Sync,Run</guilabel> button saves any script
          file changes to disk, makes the script active, synchronizes the GUI
          with the script, and executes the script.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save As Button</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>When you click <guilabel>Save As</guilabel>, GMAT displays the
          <guilabel>Choose A File</guilabel> dialog box and allows you to save
          the script using a new file name. After saving, GMAT loads the
          script into the GUI, making the new file the active script.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Close</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>Close</guilabel> button closes the script
          editor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>GUI/Script Interface Interactions and Rules</title>

    <para>The GMAT desktop supports both a script interface and a GUI
    interface and these interfaces are designed to be consistent with each
    other. You can think of the script and GUI as different "views" of the
    same data: the resources and the mission command sequence. GMAT allows you
    to switch between views (script and GUI) and have the same view open in an
    editable state simultaneously. Below we describe the behavior,
    interactions, and rules of the script and GUI interfaces so you can avoid
    confusion and potential loss of data.</para>

    <section xml:id="GuiScriptInteractionsAndSynchronization">
      <title>GUI/Script Interactions and Synchronization</title>

      <para>GMAT allows you to simultaneously edit both the script file
      representation and the GUI representation of your mission. It is
      possible to make inconsistent changes in these representations. The
      <guilabel>GUI/Script Sync Status</guilabel> window located in the
      toolbar indicates the state of the two representations. On the Mac, the
      status is indicated in abbreviated form in the left-hand toolbar.
      <guilabel>Synchronized</guilabel> (green) indicates that the script and
      GUI contain the same information. <guilabel>GUI Modified</guilabel>
      (yellow) indicates that there are changes in the GUI that have not been
      saved to the script. <guilabel>Script Modified</guilabel> (yellow)
      indicates that there are changes in the script that have not been loaded
      into the GUI. <guilabel>Unsynchronized</guilabel> (red) indicates that
      there are changes in both the script and the GUI.</para>

      <caution>
        <para>GMAT will not attempt to merge or resolve simultaneous changes
        in the Script and GUI and you must choose which representation to save
        if you have made changes in both interfaces.</para>
      </caution>

      <para>The <guiicon>Save</guiicon> button in the toolbar saves the GUI
      representation over the script. The <guibutton>Save,Sync</guibutton>
      button on the script editor saves the script representation and loads it
      into the GUI.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How the GUI Maps to a Script</title>

      <para>Clicking the <guilabel>Save</guilabel> button in the toolbar saves
      the GUI representation to the script file; this is the same file you
      edit when working in the script editor. GUI items that appear in the
      <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree appear before the
      <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command in a script file and
      are written in a predefined order. GUI items that appear in the Mission
      Tree appear after the <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command
      in a script file in the same order as they appear in the GUI.</para>

      <caution>
        <para>If you have a script file that has custom formatting such as
        spacing and data organization, you should work exclusively in the
        script. If you load your script into the GUI, then click
        <guilabel>Save</guilabel> in the toolbar, you will lose the formatting
        of your script. (You will not, however, lose the data.)</para>
      </caution>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How the Script Maps to the GUI</title>

      <para>Clicking the <guilabel>Save,Sync</guilabel> button on the script
      editor saves the script representation and loads it into the GUI. When
      you work in a GMAT script, you work in the raw file that GMAT reads and
      writes. Each script file must contain a command called
      <function>BeginMissionSequence</function>. Script lines that appear
      before the <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command create and
      configure models and this data will appear in the
      <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree in the GUI. Script lines that appear
      after the <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command define your
      mission sequence and appear in the <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tree in
      the GUI. Here is a brief script example to illustrate:</para>

      <programlisting>Create Spacecraft Sat
Sat.X = 3000
BeginMissionSequence
Sat.X = 1000</programlisting>

      <para>The line <code>Sat.X = 3000</code> sets the x-component of the
      Cartesian state to 3000; this value will appear on the
      <guilabel>Orbit</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Spacecraft</guilabel>
      dialog box. However, because the line <code>Sat.X = 1000</code> appears
      after the <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command, the line
      <code>Sat.X = 1000</code> will appear as an assignment command in the
      <guilabel>Mission</guilabel> tree in the GUI.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basic Script Syntax Rules</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each script file must contain one and only one
          <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>GMAT commands are not allowed before the
          <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You cannot use inline math statements (equations) before the
          <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command in a script file.
          (GMAT considers in-line math statements to be an assignment command.
          You cannot use equations in the <guilabel>Resources</guilabel> tree,
          so you also cannot use equations before the
          <function>BeginMissionSequence</function> command.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the GUI, you can only use in-line math statements in an
          assignment command. So, you cannot type <userinput>3000 +
          4000</userinput> or <userinput>Sat.Y - 8</userinput> in the text box
          for setting a spacecraft’s dry mass.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>GMAT’s script language is case-sensitive.</para>

          <para>For a more complete discussion of GMAT's script language, see
          the <xref linkend="ScriptLanguage"/> documentation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
