<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Solar System</title>

  <para>This was created using the June 9,2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>This folder, found if the Solar System folder itself is
    double-clicked, enables the user to determine where he gets his data on
    the movements of planets, how often it updates, and how accurate the data
    is.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>CelestialBodies, BaryCenter, and Libration Point</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The position and data on all these depend on the source of
              the Solar System data and how often it is updated.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
		
        <listitem>
          <para>Propagator</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>How often the position of the planetary bodies are updated
              will have an impact on how a spacecraft will propagate.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
		
        <listitem>
          <para>Spacecraft</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A number of parameters of a spacecraft are based off the
              position of the planets</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the GUI</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>EphemerisSource</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The EphemerisSource field allows the user to select the
            source used for planetary ephemerides. The source is used globally
            whenever planetary ephemeris information is required.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
	  
      <listitem>
        <para>EphemerisUpdateInterval</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The EphemerisUpdateInterval is used to set how often
            planetary positions are updated when calculating accelerations
            during propagation. For low-Earth orbits, EphemerisUpdateInterval
            can be set to around 60 for faster numerical integration with
            little effect on the accuracy of the propagation. For deep space
            propagation, EphemerisUpdateInterval should be set to zero.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
	  
      <listitem>
        <para>UseTTForEphemeris</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>GMAT uses time in the TDB system as the default time system
            in the JPL ephemeris files. However, often it is possible to use
            time in the TT time system, without significant difference in
            propagation accuracy. (TT and TDB are within 1 millisecond of each
            other). The advantage to using TT is that it avoids the
            transformation from TT to TDB and therefore orbit propagation will
            execute faster. The UseTTForEphemeris field allows the user to
            choose between the default of TDB in the ephemeris files
            (UseTTForEphemeris=false), or TT in the ephemeris files
            (UseTTForEphemeris = true).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
	  
      <listitem>
        <para>EphemerisFile</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The EphemerisFile field allows the user to specify the
            location and name of the file for each type of ephemeris GMAT
            supports. For example, if Ephemeris is set to DE405, you can set
            the path for a DE405 file using SolarSystem.EphemerisFile =
            c:/MyPath/MyDE405.file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
	  
      <listitem>
        <para>AnalyticModel</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the $NAME OF OBJECT OR
        COMMAND$ Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="???"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the $NAME OF OBJECT OR
          COMMAND$ Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>EphemerisSource</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: DE405.</para> <para>Options: [DE405,DE200,
            SLP, Analytic]</para> <para>The EphemerisSourcefield allows the
            user to select the source used for planetaryephemerides. The
            source is used globally whenever planetaryephemeris information is
            required. </para> <para>Units: None.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Ephemeris UpdateInterval</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0.</para> <para>Options: [ Real Number ≥
            0]</para> <para>The EphemerisUpdateInterval is used to set
            howoften planetary positions are updated when calculating
            accelerationsduring propagation. For low-Earth
            orbits,EphemerisUpdateInterval can be set to around 60 for
            fasternumerical integration with little effect on the accuracy of
            thepropagation. For deep space propagation,EphemerisUpdateInterval
            should be set to zero.</para> <para>Units: sec.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>UseTTForEphemeris</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: false.</para> <para>Options: [true,
            false]</para> <para>GMAT uses time in the TDB system as thedefault
            time system in the JPL ephemeris files. However, often itis
            possible to use time in the TT time system, without
            significantdifference in propagation accuracy. (TT and TDB are
            within 1millisecond of each other). The advantage to using TT is
            that itavoids the transformation from TT to TDB and therefore
            orbitpropagation will execute faster. The UseTTForEphemeris
            fieldallows the user to choose between the default of TDB in
            theephemeris files (UseTTForEphemeris=false), or TT in
            theephemeris files (UseTTForEphemeris = true). </para>
            <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>EphemerisFile</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: Same as startup file.</para> <para>Options:[
            Filepath and file name consistent with operating system ]</para>
            <para>The EphemerisFile field allows the user to specify the
            locationand name of the file for each type of ephemeris GMAT
            supports. Forexample, if Ephemeris is set to DE405, you can set
            thepath for a DE405 file using SolarSystem.EphemerisFile
            =c:/MyPath/MyDE405.file.</para> <para> Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>AnalyticModel</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: LowFidelity.</para> <para>Options:
            [LowFidelity]: </para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
