<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

<title>XYPlot</title>
<para>This was created using the June 18, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>
<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<para>The XY Plot is a graph under the Plots/Reports folder in the resource tree that plots data onto the X and Y axes of the graph. Any two parameters can be chosen to plot from the Parameter Select dialog box when the View radio button is clicked.  The plot has the capability to be turned on and/or off throughout the mission if desirable.  </para>
<section>
<title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Spacecraft </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Spacecraft interact with an XY Plot throughout the entire mission.  The data retrieved from the spacecraft, as it carries out the command, is what gets plotted onto the graph. </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Toggle Command</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A Toggle can be inserted into the mission sequence to control when the XY Plot is to plot data by subscribing it to the Toggle list. If it is necessary to only plot data at a certain point during the mission, besides at the beginning or end points, then two Toggle commands can be added to switch it on and off.   </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the GUI</title>
<para>The XY Plots dialog box has a group box, two fields, and a couple View buttons that open the Parameter Select dialog box.  When the mission is run, the XY Plot will set aside a portion of the screen for itself alongside any other plots created in the resource tree.   </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Options - Group Box</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This group box located on the far left column gives the options of whether the plot shows the faint background grid, none, some, or all of the solver iterations, the color of the plotted data, or whether the plot even appears while running the mission.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Selected X - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This field is where an X parameter is chosen to be plotted on the X axes.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Selected Y - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This field is where an Y parameter is chosen to be plotted on the Y axes.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<screenshot><info><title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the XY Plot Dialog Box</title></info><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center"
fileref="???"></imagedata></imageobject>
<caption><para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the XY Plot Dialog Box</para></caption></mediaobject></screenshot>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the script</title>
<section>
<title>Script Syntax</title>
<programlisting><code>Create XYPlot XYPlot1;
GMAT XYPlot1.SolverIterations = Current;
GMAT XYPlot1.IndVar = Sat.A1ModJulian;
GMAT XYPlot1.Add = {Sat.EarthMJ2000Eq.X};
GMAT XYPlot1.Grid = On;
GMAT XYPlot1.ShowPlot = true;
</code></programlisting>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reference Table</title>
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>IndVar</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: DefaultSC.A1ModJulian</para>
<para>Options: { Any user variable, array element, or spacecraft parameter }</para>
<para>The IndVar field allows the user to define the independent variable for an xy-plot. Only one variable can be defined as an independent variable. For example, the line MyXYPlot.IndVar = DefaultSC.A1ModJulian sets the independent variable to be the epoch of DefaultSC in the A1 time system and modified Julian format.</para>
<para>Units: N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Add</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: DefaultSC.EarthMJ2000Eq.X.</para>
<para>Options: { Any user variable, array element, or spacecraft parameter }</para>
<para>The Add field allows the user to add dependent variables to an xy-plot. All dependent variables are plotted on the y-axisvs the independent variable defined by IndVar. To define multiple dependent variables, they should be included in curly braces. For example,  MyXYPlot.Add = DefaultSC.EarthMJ2000Eq.Y , DefaultSC.EarthMJ2000Eq.Z. The GUI's Selected field is the equivalent of the script's Add field.  In the event of no Add command or no objects in the Selected field, GMAT should run without the XYPlot and a warning message displayed in the message window. The following warning message is sufficient: XYPlot will be turned off. No object has been selected for plotting.</para>
<para>Units: N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Grid</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: On.</para>
<para>Options: { On, Off }</para>
<para>When the Grid field is set to On, then a grid is drawn on an xy-plot. When the Grid field is set to Off, then a grid is not drawn.</para>
<para>    Units: N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>SolverIterations</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: Off. </para>
<para>Options: { On, Off } </para>
<para>The SolverIterations field determines whether or not perturbed trajectories are plotted during a solver (Targeter, Optimize) sequence.  When SolverIterations is set to On, solver iterations are shown on the plot. When SolverIterations is set to Off,  solver iterations are not shown on the plot.</para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>ShowPlot</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: true.</para>
<para>Options: { true, false }</para>
<para>The ShowPlot field allows the user to turn off a plot for a particular run, without deleting the plot object, or removing it from the script.  If you select true, then the plot will be shown.  If you select false, then the plot will not be shown. </para>
<para>Units: N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>