<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="Achieve" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Achieve</title>

  <para>This was created using the June 18, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The purpose of the Achieve command is to define a goal for the
    spacecraft to reach at some point in its trajectory. The goal must have a
    corresponding value and tolerance so the differential corrector can solve
    for the best solution during the spacecraft's flight. To define a goal, a
    property must be chosen out of the Parameter Select dialog box along with
    the correct components in the other fields. The command can only be
    appended within a targeting sequence and must be accompanied and preceeded
    by a Vary, Maneuver, and Propagate command.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Spacecraft</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>In order to achieve a goal at all, a spacecraft must exist
              so GMAT has something to propagate and maneuver.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Differential Corrector</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A differential corrector is needed to calculate and solve
              for the goal to be achieved.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Vary Command</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>This command pulls variables into a targeting sequence for
              GMAT to know what parameters are being changed. As soon as a
              change occurs in a parameter, the differential corrector solves
              for the best trajectory using that data in order to achieve a
              goal.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maneuver Command</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Changing any parameter of the spacecraft requires a
              Maneuver command and some sort of burn, so this, too, is an
              essential part of the Achieve command</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Burn</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Changing parameters by means of maneuvering requires a
              burn to do so, and in this process the spacecraft is achieving a
              goal.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propagate Command</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>To achieve a goal, the spacecraft must be moving and,
              thus, be executing a Propagate command.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the GUI</title>

    <para>The Achieve command dialog box has four fields to consider including
    a drop down menu for the Solver. By clicking on the View buttons,
    parameters from the Parameter Select dialog box can be chosen and entered
    in as a goal. Once a legitimate value and tolerance are entered for the
    parameter, the command is complete and is ready to run in the
    mission.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Solver - Drop Down Menu</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>All of the differential correctors created are located in
            this menu to choose from for the Achieve command to utilize during
            operation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Goal - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choosing a goal requires an object, parameter, and
            potentially a coordinate system to be highlighted in the Parameter
            Select dialog box. Once all are selected, the field will read
            (spacecraft).(coordinate system).(parameter), depending on the
            need for a coordinate system. If a system is not required, the
            field will read (spacecraft).(parameter).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Value - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A number is to be entered here that corresponds to the goal
            chosen. If the value does not make sense, the mission will run,
            but it will not converge. Also, depending on the situation, excess
            data points may be created and will produce the same
            outcome.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tolerance - Field</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The tolerance tells GMAT how lenient the differential
            corrector should be when accepting solutions around the value
            entered in previous field.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Achieve Command
        Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="???"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Achieve Command
          Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the script</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script Syntax</title>

      <programlisting><code>Achieve SolverName(Goal) = Arg1, Tolerance = Arg2</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Goal</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: DefaultSC.Earth.RMAG.</para> <para>Options:
            { Spacecraft parameter, Array element, Variable, or any other
            single element user defined parameter, excluding numbers }</para>
            <para>The option allows the user to select any single element user
            defined parameter, except a number, to Achieve.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Arg1</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 42165.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number,
            Array element, Variable, or any user defined parameter that obeys
            the conditions of Chapter~\\ref\{Ch:ObjectsNResources\} for the
            selected } </para> <para>The Arg1 option is the desired value for
            after the solver has converged.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Tolerance</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 0.1.</para> <para>Options: { Real Number,
            Array element, Variable, or any user defined parameter &gt; 0
            }</para> <para>The Tolerance option sets Arg2. Arg2 is the
            convergence tolerance for Arg1.</para> <para>Units:
            N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>SolverName</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: DefaultDC.</para> <para>Options: { Any user
            defined differential corrector }</para> <para>The SolverName
            option allows the user to choose which solver to assign to the
            Achieve command. </para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
