<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>For</title>

  <para>This was created using the June 9, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The for loop is a control flow statement that allows portions of
    code to be executed iteratively using an explicit loop variable
    (Wikipedia). GMAT for loops are three-expression loops that allow the user
    to set the initial value of the loop variable, its increment, and the test
    to exit the loop. A parameter must be defined explicitly using a Create
    Variable statement or GUI equivalent before it can be used in a for loop
    command statement. The parameters used to define Start, Increment, and End
    can be any of the following GMAT parameters: numeric literal (real
    number), variable, array element, object property.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interfaces</title>

    <para>The GUI for the For Loop command is divided into four
    sections.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The first section, the index, is where the counter variable name
        is displayed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The second section, the start, is the number with which the
        counter variable is first stored with.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The third section, the increment, is the value that the counter
        variable will change by each time the program goes through the
        loop.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The fourth section, the end, is the value of the counter
        variable when the loop is exited.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
        <title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the For Loop command
        Dialog Box</title>
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="???"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the For Loop command
          Dialog Box</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Script Syntax</title>

      <para>(Simple For Loop)</para>

      <programlisting><code>For Variable = Start:End;

EndFor; }</code></programlisting>

      <para>(Expanded For Loop)</para>

      <programlisting><code>For Variable = Start:Increment:End;

EndFor;</code></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Script Examples</title>

      <programlisting><code>% Output the value of the For loop Variable to a file
For I = 1:1:10;
GMAT testVar = I;
Report DefaultReportFile I;
EndFor;</code></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reference Table</title>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Variable</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: No Default.</para> <para>Options:[ Variable
            ]</para> <para>The Variable field allows the user to define the
            variable that to be incremented during the loop process.</para>
            <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Start</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 1.</para> <para>Options: [ Real Number,
            Array element, Variable, or any user defined parameter ].</para>
            <para>The Start option allows the user to set the starting value
            of the For Loop.</para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Increment</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 1.</para> <para>Options: [ Real Number,
            Array element, Variable, or any user defined parameter ].</para>
            <para>The Increment option allows the user to set the increment
            value of the For Loop. When the increment value is not included in
            a for loop statement, the default value is used.</para>
            <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>End</para></entry>

            <entry><para>Default: 10. </para> <para>Options: [ Real Number,
            Array, Variable, or any user defined parameter ]. </para>
            <para>The End option allows the user to set the ending value of
            the For Loop. </para> <para>Units: N/A.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Objects and Command Interactions</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>For Loop Behavior</title>

    <para>When the Increment option is left out of the script syntax the
    default value is used. If an Increment value of 0 is used, the For Loop
    should not execute but GMAT should continue to run. If End&gt;Start and
    Increment&lt;0, then the For Loop should not execute. If Start&gt;End and
    Increment&gt;0, then the For Loop should not execute. End can be equal to
    Start, but the For Loop will not execute.</para>
  </section>
</section>
