<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

<title>Propagate</title>
<para>This was created using the June 9, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>
<section>
<title>Overview of the Propagate Command</title>
<para>The Propagate Command is a very important one and will be covered in this section.  Basically, Propagate will take the given spacecraft and, using the Propagat''or'' specified as its guide, make it travel until the given condition is met whether it be a location or something else such as elapsed time.</para>
<section>
<title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Spacecraft</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>It is pretty intuitive that you would need to choose a spacecraft to propagate in order to use the command.  Basically, once you create a spacecraft in the resource tree, it will appear as a spacecraft that you can propagate using this command.  Note that you can propagate several spacecraft using the same Propagate command.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Formation</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The same way that you can propagate a Spacecraft, you can propagate a group of spacecraft that are assigned to a Formation.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Propagator</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Just as the propagate command needs a spacecraft to propagate, it also needs a propagator that has the parameters of propagation.  This basically means that you must setup a propagator that governs the spacecraft as it travels through space.  This includes what gravity is affecting it, as well as drag and solar radiation pressure.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Parameters</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Whatever parameters of object type Spacecraft, Variable, or Array, that are present within the Parameter Select Dialog box, are available to this field.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the Propagate Command in the GUI</title>
<para>The Propagate Command dialog box is split into two sections.  The first of these is the Propagators and Spacecraft Group Box.  It is where you specify which Propagator the Propagate Command will use.  It is also where you specify which spacecraft to propagate.  The next Groups Box is the Stopping Conditions.  This Box is where you set the condition that will end the propagation of the spacecraft.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Propagators and Spacecraft - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Propagate Mode - Drop Down Menu</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This is where you set what mode you want the Propagator to use, None or Synchronized</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Backwards Propagation - Check Box</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Checking this box will make the spacecraft travel backwards until the given stopping condition is met.  Examples of this would make a spacecraft will travel backwards in its orbit or travel backwards in  time for a given period.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Backwards propagation can be useful if you know where a spacecraft must be at the end of its journey and you must see what possible path it can take to reach that objective.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Propagator - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This specifies the Propagator that the Propagate Command uses</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Spacecraft List - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This is where the spacecraft that the Propagate Command is operating upon is specified.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multiple Spacecraft may be entered here with their trajectories all being governed by the given propagator.  If they are, they may be synchronized as given in the script example below.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Besides Spacecraft, entire formations may be entered here for propagation.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Stopping Conditions - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Stop Tolerance - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This is how close you allow GMAT to be off from the given stopping condition.  The smaller the number, the greater the precision.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Parameter - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This is what the Propagate Command will stop on.  It can be set as a date, a location in orbit, or any other option given in the Parameter Select Dialog Box.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multiple stopping conditions may be chosen.  GMAT will stop propagation at the earliest met parameter.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Condition - Field</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>If the Parameter you set requires a value, such as a number of elapsed days, then you enter it here.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>{img src=show_image.php?name=PropagateCommandMain align="center"}</para>
<para>
<screenshot><info><title></title></info><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center"
fileref="???"></imagedata></imageobject>
<caption><para></para></caption></mediaobject></screenshot></para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the Propagate Command in the script</title>
<section>
<title>Script Syntax</title>
<programlisting><code><font face="courier new">Propagate Mode BackProp <I>PropagatorName</I>(SatList1,fStopCondList1g) ...
<I>BackPropPropagator</I>Name (SatListN, {StopCondList})</font>
</code></programlisting>
</section>
<section>
<title>Script Examples</title>
<programlisting><code>% Single spacecraft propagation with one stopping condition

<para>% Syntax #1
</para><font face="courier new">Propagate DefaultProp(DefaultSC, {DefaultSC.ElapsedSecs = 8640.0});</font>

% Single spacecraft propagation with one stopping condition

<para>% Syntax #2
</para><font face="courier new">Propagate DefaultProp(DefaultSC) {DefaultSC.ElapsedSecs = 8640.0};</font>

% Single spacecraft propagation by one integration step
<font face="courier new">Propagate DefaultProp(DefaultSC);</font>

% Multiple spacecraft propagation by one integration step
<font face="courier new">Propagate DefaultProp(Sat1, Sat2, Sat3);</font>

% Single formation propagation by one integration step
<font face="courier new">Propagate DefaultProp(DefaultFormation);</font>

% Single spacecraft backwards propagation by one integration step
<font face="courier new">Propagate Backwards DefaultProp(DefaultSC);</font>

% Two spacecraft synchronized propagation with one stopping condition
<font face="courier new">Propagate Synchronized DefaultProp(Sat1, Sat2, {DefaultSC.ElapsedSecs = 8640.0});</font>

% Multiple spacecraft propagation with multiple stopping conditions and propagation settings

<para>% Syntax #1
</para><font face="courier new">Propagate Prop1(Sat1,Sat2, {Sat1.ElapsedSecs = 8640.0, Sat2.MA = 90}) ...</font>
<font face="courier new">Prop2(Sat3, {Sat3.TA = 0.0});</font>

% Multiple spacecraft propagation with multiple stopping conditions and propagation settings

<para>% Syntax #2
</para><font face="courier new">Propagate Prop1(Sat1,Sat2) {Sat1.ElapsedSecs = 8640.0, Sat2.MA = 90} ...</font>
<font face="courier new">Prop2(Sat3), {Sat3.TA = 0.0};</font>
</code></programlisting>
<para>	</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reference Table</title>
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>        BackProp</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: None</para>
<para>	Options: { Backwards or None }</para>
<para>	The BackProp option allows the user to set the flag to enable or disable backwards propagation for all spacecraft in the SatListN option. The Backward Propagation GUI check box field stores all the data in BackProp. A check indicates backward propagation is enabled and no check indicates forward propagation. In the script, BackProp can be the word Backwards for backward propagation or blank for forward propagation.</para>
<para>	Units: N/A</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>	Mode</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: None</para>
<para>	Options: { Synchronized or None }</para>
<para>    The Mode option allows the user to set the propagation mode for the propagator that will affect all of the spacecraft added to the SatListN option. For example, if synchronized is selected, all spacecraft are propagated at the same step size. The Propagate Mode GUI field stores all the data in Mode. In the script, Mode is left blank for the None option and the text of the other options available is used for their respective modes.</para>
<para>	Units: N/A</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>	<I>PropagatorName</I></para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: DefaultProp</para>
<para>	Options: { Default propagator or any user-defined propagator }</para>
<para>	The <I>PropagatorName</I> option allows the user to select a user defined propagator to use in spacecraft and/or formation propagation. The Propagator GUI field stores all the data in <I>PropagatorName</I>.</para>
<para>	Units: N/A</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>	SatListN</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: DefaultSC</para>
<para>	Options: { Any existing spacecraft or formations, not being propagated by another propagator in the same Propagate event.  Multiple spacecraft must be expressed in a comma delimited list format. }</para>
<para>	The SatListN option allows the user to enter all the satellites and/or formations they want to propagate using the <I>PropagatorName</I> propagator settings. The Spacecraft List GUI field stores all the data in SatListN.</para>
<para>	Units: N/A</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>	StopCondListN	/Parameter</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: DefaultSC.ElapsedSecs =</para>
<para>	Options: { Any single element user accessible spacecraft parameter followed by an equal sign }</para>
<para>	The StopCondListN option allows the user to enter all the parameters used for the propagator stopping condition. See the StopCondListN/Condition Option/Field for additional details to the StopCondListN option.</para>
<para>	Units: N/A</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>	StopCondListN	/Condition</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>	Default: 8640.0</para>
<para>	Options: { Real Number, Array element, Variable, spacecraft parameter, or any user defined parameter }.</para>
<para>	The StopCondListN option allows the user to enter the propagator stopping condition's value for the StopCondListN Parameter field.</para>
<para>	Units: Dependant on the condition selected.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>