<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

<title>Attitude Tab</title>
<para>This was created using the June 18, 2008 build of GMAT.</para>
<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<para>${P}In this section, you will write a brief summary of what the object or command does and how it works in basic terms.{P}$  </para>
<section>
<title>Listing of Objects and Commands that interact</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Spacecraft</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>In order to access the attitude controls a spacecraft must exist.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Coordinate System</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The Attitude Model supplies the option of using any system either created or preexisting in the project to use when defining a spacecraft's attitude during the mission.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the GUI</title>
<para>${P}This Section will describe the layout of the GUI dialog box, mostly at the group box level, and give a brief overview of what can be changed here.{P}$</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Group Box</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Attitude Model - Drop Down Menu</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Either a fixed or spinning coordinate system is chosen here to tell GMAT how to calculate spacecraft attitude properties.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Coordinate System - Drop Down Menu</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Any previously existing system or any created in the project are available to choose from.  The system selected will depend on the mission information desired and is based on allowed error and other calculations.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Euler Angle Sequence - Drop Down Menu</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>All combinations of Euler Angles are available here.  The sequence chosen is dependent upon the type of information needed.  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Attitude Initial Conditions - Group Box</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Attitude Rate Initial Conditions - Group Box</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<screenshot><info><title>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Spacecraft Attitude Dialog Box</title></info><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center"
fileref="???"></imagedata></imageobject>
<caption><para>Figure: Default Name and Settings for the Spacecraft Attitude Dialog Box</para></caption></mediaobject></screenshot>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using the script</title>
<section>
<title>Script Syntax</title>
<programlisting><code>Create Spacecraft Spacecraft1;
GMAT Spacecraft1.DateFormat = TAIModJulian;
GMAT Spacecraft1.Epoch = '21545.000000000';
GMAT Spacecraft1.CoordinateSystem = EarthMJ2000Eq;
GMAT Spacecraft1.DisplayStateType = Cartesian;
GMAT Spacecraft1.X = 7100;
GMAT Spacecraft1.Y = 0;
GMAT Spacecraft1.Z = 1300;
GMAT Spacecraft1.VX = 0;
GMAT Spacecraft1.VY = 7.35;
GMAT Spacecraft1.VZ = 1;
GMAT Spacecraft1.DryMass = 850;
GMAT Spacecraft1.Cd = 2.2;
GMAT Spacecraft1.Cr = 1.8;
</code></programlisting>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reference Table</title>
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>Attitude Mode</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default:  CSFixed.</para>
<para>Options: { CSFixed, Spinner }</para>
<para>The AttitudeMode mode field allows the user to specify the attitude dynamics model to be used by GMAT to propagate a spacecraft's attitude.  The attitude dynamics model uses the initial attitude state and the algorithm associated with AttitudeMode to advance the attitude state in time.</para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Attitude Coordinate System</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: EarthMJ2000Eq.</para>
<para>Options: { EarthMJ2000Eq, EarthMJ2000Ec, EarthMJ2000Eq, or any user defined system }A spacecraft's initial body axes orientation as defined by the quaternions or some other parameterizations are expressed with respect to the AttitudeCoordinateSystem.  Unlike an orbit state, an attitude state is really information that uniquely defines a rotation matrix.  A spacecraft's attitude is the orientation of the spacecraft's body-fixed frame with respect to the inertial frame. However, it is often more convenient to define the initial attitude with respect to an intermediate frame than with respect to an inertial frame.  The Attitude CoordinateSystem allows the user to define the initial orientation of a spacecraft's body axes, with respect to any frame GMAT knows how to calculate.  </para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Attitude StateType</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: EulerAngles.</para>
<para>Options: { EulerAngles, Quaternions, DCM }</para>
<para>The AttitudeStateType field allows the user to choose among different attitude parameterizations when defining the attitude initial conditions.</para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Attitude Rate StateType</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: EulerAngleRates.</para>
<para>Options: { EulerAngleRates, AngularVelocity }</para>
<para>The AttitudeRateStateType field allows the user to define the attitude parameterization to be used in defining the initial attitude rate.</para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Euler Angle Sequence</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 312.</para>
<para>Options: { 123, 132, 121, 131, 213, 231, 212, 232, 312, 321, 313, 323 }</para>
<para>The EulerAngleSequence field allows the user to define the Euler sequence used in rotating from the body-fixed to the inertial axes.  For example, if EulerAngleSequence is selected as 321, then the first rotation is a 3 rotation through EulerAngle1, the second rotation is a 2 rotation through EulerAngle2, and the third rotation is a 1 rotation through EulerAngle3.</para>
<para>Units:  N/A.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable> 
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle1</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number } </para>
<para>EulerAngle1 is one of three Euler angles that can be used to define the initial conditions of a spacecraft.  EulerAngle1 corresponds to the first rotation performed in the sequence that goes from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  For example, if the EulerAngleSequence field is set to 321, the first rotation from the body to the inertial frame would be a 3-rotation throughEulerAngle1.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle2</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>EulerAngle2 is one of three Euler angles that can be used to define the initial conditions of a spacecraft.  EulerAngle2 corresponds to the second rotation performed in the sequence that goes from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  For example, if the EulerAngleSequence field is set to 321, the second rotation from the body to the inertial frame would be a 2-rotation through EulerAngle2.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle3</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>EulerAngle3 is one of three Euler angles that can be used to define the initial conditions of a spacecraft.  EulerAngle3 corresponds to the third rotation performed in the sequence that goes from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  For example, if the EulerAngleSequence field is set to 321, the third rotation from the body to the inertial frame would be a 1-rotation through EulerAngle3.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>q1</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The q1 parameter is the first element of the quaternion.  GMAT normalizes the quaternion to be of length 1.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>q2</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The q2 parameter is the second element of the quaternion.GMAT normalizes the quaternion to be of length 1.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>q3</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The q3 parameter is the third element of the quaternion.  GMAT normalizes the quaternion to be of length 1.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>q4</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 1.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The q4 parameter is the fourth element of the quaternion. GMAT normalizes the quaternion to be of length 1.</para>
<para>Units:  degrees.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>DCM11</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 1.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The DCM11 parameter is the upper left component of the direction cosine matrix that rotates from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  GMAT normalizes the attitude matrix to have a determinant of 1.  The default DCM matrix is the identity matrix.</para>
<para>Units:  None.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>DCM12</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The DCM12 parameter is the R_{12} component of the direction cosine matrix that rotates from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  GMAT normalizes the attitude matrix to have a determinant of 1.  The default DCM matrix is the identity matrix.</para>
<para>Units:  None.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>DCM33</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 1.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The DCM33 parameter is the R_{33} component of the direction cosine matrix that rotates from the spacecraft body frame to the inertial frame.  GMAT normalizes the attitude matrix to have a determinant of 1.  The default DCM matrix is the identity matrix.</para>
<para>Units:  None.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle Rate1</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The EulerAngleRate1 defines the time-rate-of-change of EulerAngle1, expressed in the the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.  </para>
<para>Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle Rate2</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The EulerAngleRate2 defines the time-rate-of-change of EulerAngle2, expressed in the the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.  Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>EulerAngle Rate3</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The EulerAngleRate3 defines the time-rate-of-change of EulerAngle3, expressed in the the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.  </para>
<para>Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Angular VelocityX</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The AngularVelocityX component is the x-component of the spacecraft's body axes with respect to the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.</para>
<para>Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Angular VelocityY</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The AngularVelocityY component is the y-component of the spacecraft's body axes with respect to the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.</para>
<para>Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Angular VelocityZ</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Default: 0.</para>
<para>Options: { Real Number }</para>
<para>The AngularVelocityZ component is the z-component of the spacecraft's body axes with respect to the system defined by AttitudeCoordinateSystem.</para>
<para>Units:  deg/sec.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable> 
</section>
</section>